<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Truth outweighing error, or, An ansvver to a treatise lately published by J.B. entituled, A confession of his faith and a reason of his practice, or, With who he can, and with who he cannot hold church-fellowship ... by John Denne ...</title>
            <author>J. D. (John Denne)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1673</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 189 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 64 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A35667</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D1027</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11873</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13120483</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13120483</idno>
            <idno type="VID">97824</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A35667)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 97824)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 414:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Truth outweighing error, or, An ansvver to a treatise lately published by J.B. entituled, A confession of his faith and a reason of his practice, or, With who he can, and with who he cannot hold church-fellowship ... by John Denne ...</title>
                  <author>J. D. (John Denne)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>124, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author, and are to be sold by F. Smith ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1673.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata on p. 124.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement [3] p. at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bunyan, John, 1628-1688. --  Confession of my faith and a reason of my practice.</term>
               <term>Fellowship --  Religious aspects.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:97824:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97824:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Truth outweighing Error:</hi> Or, An ANSVVER TO A <hi>Treatiſe</hi> lately publiſhed by <hi>J. B.</hi> Entituled, <hi>A Confeſsion of his Faith,</hi> AND <hi>A Reaſon of his Practice.</hi> OR, With <hi>who</hi> he can, and with <hi>who</hi> he cannot hold <hi>Church-Fellowſhip,</hi> or the <hi>Communion of Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>John Denne,</hi> a Servant of the Church.</p>
            <q>
               <p>He that is firſt in his own Cauſe, ſeemeth juſt; but his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour cometh and ſearcheth him,
<bibl>Prov. 18.17.</bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>For it was not an Enemy that reproached me, then I could have born it,
<bibl>Pſal. 55.12.</bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sed nullum eſt Atrocius vulnus quam defectio amici.</hi>
                  <bibl>Sophocles.</bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for the <hi>Author,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>F. Smith,</hi> at the Elephant and Caſtle near the <hi>Royal-Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change</hi> in <hi>Cornhil,</hi> and at the ſame ſign the firſt ſhop with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Temple-Bar,</hi> 1673.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:97824:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97824:2"/>
            <head>To the Church of God; in God the Father and his Son Jeſus Chriſt, eſpecially to my well beloved Brethren in the Counties of <hi>Huntington</hi> and <hi>Cambridge:</hi> Grace, Mercy, and Peace be multiplied unto you from God the Father, and the Lord Jeſus Christ the Son of the Father in Truth and Love.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dearly Beloved,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is once, yea twice declared in the Book of <hi>Job,</hi> That when the Sons of God came to preſent themſelves before the Lord, Satan came alſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them; ſurely, not only to eſpy what miſcarriage might give him advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage againſt them, but alſo to endeavour their ſubverſion by the crafty inſinuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of himſelf, and miniſters, ſtirred up to that end; and no marvel, for if he durſt preſume to practiſe the ſame againſt our bleſſed Saviour, we may more aſſuredly expect his ſubtilty and puiſſance to be
<pb facs="tcp:97824:3"/>
bent againſt us: wherefore Diligence and Sobriety is required, (1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.8.) that by the one you may avoid giving him occaſion againſt you; and by the other diſcover his crafty devices, although car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried on by fair pretences, like a Wolf in Sheeps-cloathing, making uſe therefore of ſome of your own ſelves, according to the words of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul, (Acts</hi> 20.29.) which (as heretofore) is this day ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parently verified; and that (amongſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers) particularly in that Book preſented to the World by <hi>J. Bunyan,</hi> entituled, <hi>A Confeſſion of his Faith, and the reaſon of his practice touching Church-fellowſhip:</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, (amongſt other things) he endeavours the vilifying (the ready way for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpation) of the Ordinance of <hi>Water-Baptiſm,</hi> and that under the ſpecious pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences of <hi>Charity, Church-edification,</hi> &amp;c. that his Deſign might be ſo masked, as to be received by many conſcientious Chriſtians, who cannot (through his craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty vail) diſcover his intentions in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the aforeſaid Ordinance, which
<pb facs="tcp:97824:3"/>
he would not have us at all reſpect in the matter of Church-Communion. Which I no ſooner ſaw, but I was filled with diſpleaſure, apprehending my ſelf obliged, as once <hi>Phineas</hi> was (in a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter whereunto this is not inferiour, if the ſpiritual concern be reſpected) to mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt an holy indignation againſt the ſame, and (according to my ability) to vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate the Truth therein degraded; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon I reſolved to ſend abroad the enſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> which I now commend to you; (what is <hi>well done,</hi> expects your Approbation; and what is <hi>amiſs,</hi> your gentle Correction): withal entreating you to look to your ſelves that you may not be enſnared; hold faſt the form of ſound words, leſt that otherwiſe you be unawares beguiled; retain alwayes a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verent eſteem of God's Ordinances. Which if you do not, you will ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be ſurprized by that Adverſary, who goeth about like a roaring Lion ſeeking whom he may devour; keep cloſe to the Holy Scriptures, continue inſtant in
<pb facs="tcp:97824:4"/>
Prayer, and that for me alſo, that Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, Boldneſs, and Patience may be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven me, that I may not ceaſe to ſpeak the things I have believed. Brethren, farewel, the God of Peace fill you with all Joy and Peace in believing. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your unworthy Brother in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> John Denne.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:97824:4"/>
            <head>The Epiſtle to the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IF <hi>Solomon</hi> had cauſe to ſay in his time, <hi>Eccleſ. 12.12.</hi> in making many Books there is no end, what may be ſaid in our dayes, when the World is ſo repleniſhed with Books, and thoſe <hi>pro &amp; contra,</hi> even in matters of Chriſtianity, inſomuch as the queſtion propounded by <hi>Paul, 1</hi> Cor. <hi>1.13. Is Chriſt divided?</hi> may now ſeem juſtly to be anſwered on the affirmative, or (which is rather to be conſented unto) that the prediction of Chriſt Jeſus <hi>(Matth. 24.24. That there ſhall ariſe falſe Chriſts, many coming in his Name, ſaying, Lo here, and lo there is Chriſt)</hi> is now accompliſhed, for the diſcovery of whom, and demonſtration of the Truth, that one Book (<hi>viz.</hi> the Holy Scripture) is only neceſſary, which of it ſelf is able to make a man wiſe unto Salvation, through Faith which is in Chriſt Jeſus; who there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore adviſeth the Sons of Men to ſearch the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, <hi>Joh. 5.39.</hi> becauſe they are they which do te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie of him: The conſideration wherof hath hitherto obſtructed my preſenting any thing to publick view, although divers times thereto incited, as well by the perſwaſion of ſome Friends, as the apprehenſion of the want of ſome aſſiſtance in the vindication of the Truth as it is in Jeſus, which (as formerly hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired my hand) at this time induceth me to ſtep
<pb facs="tcp:97824:5"/>
forth particularly upon the peruſal of a Treatiſe ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by <hi>J.B.</hi> entituled, <hi>A Confeſſion of his Faith, and the reaſon of his Practice touching Church-Fellowſhip:</hi> Which (although ſometime publiſhed) came lately to my view, wherein an apparent wrong and publick abuſe being offered to God and his Son Chriſt Jeſus, in his endeavouring the exploſion of the Holy Ordinance of Baptiſm; it took ſuch impreſſion within me, that I could not now forbear the preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the enſuing Treatiſe to the view of the World in anſwer thereunto, whereof it may perhaps be ſaid (as <hi>Paul</hi> of himſelf, <hi>1 Cor. 15.8.) It is born out of due time:</hi> but if ſo, I preſume wiſe Perſons will allow, that an Abortive birth, wherein there is life, muſt not be rejected; wherefore, although perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture there may be others (which I know not of) that may precede this upon the ſame account (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the priority muſt be granted): Touching this, let me ſay as <hi>(Abigail</hi> to <hi>David)</hi> Accept it as a Servant to the Servants of the Servants of our God, whereby perhaps ſome (although mean) Service may be ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, which may be advantagious in the diſcovery of Truth from the diſguiſed face of Error: Wherefore (in the Name of our Lord Jeſus) let me entreat thee to read impartially, and try diligently by the Scriptures of Truth, what thou findeſt in this follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Treatiſe declared, and the Lord give thee therein the Spirit of diſcerning; which ſhall be the earneſt Prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> John Denne.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:97824:5"/>
            <head>Truth outweighing Error, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>WHen the Woman clothed with the Sun, and the Moon under her feet, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.1. and upon her Head a Crown of twelve Stars, was with Child, and cried travelling in birth, and pained to be delivered; then there appeared, <hi>verſ.</hi> 3. a great Wonder in Heaven, <hi>viz.</hi> a great red Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon, having ſeven Heads, and ten Horns, and ſeven Crowns upon his Heads, who with his Tayl drew the third part of the Stars from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and caſt them to the Earth. This Dragon ſtood before the Woman to devour the Child as ſoon as it ſhould be brought forth: but his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes therein being fruſtrated, he endeavoured (by divers aſſaults and ſtratagems) not only the deſtruction of the Child, but alſo the Mother thereof; ſeeking ſo craftily the purſuance of his enterprize, that he was fitly termed that old Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, the Devil and Satan, <hi>verſ.</hi> 9. who by his ſubtilty deceived <hi>Eve,</hi> 2 Cor. 11.3. perſwading her, That God was not ſo much their Friend as they imagined<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for, ſaith he, <hi>God doth know that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:97824:6"/>
in the day you cat of that tree which he hath forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, your eyes ſhall be opened, and you ſhall be as Gods,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. thereby endeavouring to bring them into a diſ-eſteem of the Laws of their Creator, that ſo he might induce them to conſent to his wicked device; which craft (as then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan) is daily practiſed for the corrupting the minds of Saints from the ſimplicity that is in Chriſt, of which devices <hi>Paul</hi> was not ignorant, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.11. but underſtood the working of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, to get (in his time) an advantage of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans; ſometimes (for that purpoſe) transform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf into an Angel of Light, the eaſier to deceive mankind, and thereby to accompliſh his own deſigns; for the effecting whereof he alſo ſendeth forth Miniſters transformed into the Apoſtles of Chriſt, and Miniſters of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.15. of whom our Saviour doth admoniſh us to take heed, <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.15. as of falſe Prophets which come in Sheeps clothing, but inwardly are ravening Wolves; thereby in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timating, that it ought to be the continual care of Saints, in all Ages, to avoid ſuch, leſt that with feigned words, and fair ſpeeches, their Souls ſhould be enſnared in that crafty ſnare of Satan, wherein men become captivated at his will to their utter ruine and deſtruction. And as this we are admoniſhed of, ſo, by continued experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, the neceſſity thereof is demonſtrated. Time would fail me to relate how t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t evil one hath,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:97824:6"/>
and doth endeavour, by ſubtilty, to accompliſh what by force he cannot; That, as of old his Tail did more harm than his Horns; ſo now by the crafty inſinuations of his Miniſters, he endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voureth the violation of God's righteous Laws, in procuring, firſt, a diſeſteem thereof in the hearts of Chriſtians, that ſo they may (with the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter content) be negligent in the performance of the ſame, he well knowing what the event there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of will be, for through idleneſs of the hands the houſe falleth down; and thereby may he craftily accompliſh his wicked deſign. An In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance whereof is apparent in that little <hi>Treatiſe</hi> lately publiſhed by <hi>J. B.</hi> entituled, <hi>A Confeſſion of his Faith, and a reaſon of his Practice with who, and who not, he can have Church-fellowſhip or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of Saints:</hi> Wherein the <hi>Reader</hi> may as well diſcern the Spirit of the <hi>Author</hi> clearly demonſtrated, as his Perſon by the letters of his Name ſubſcribed; who (amongſt other things) endeavoureth to vilifie the Holy Ordinance of <hi>Water-Baptiſm,</hi> that thereby he might bring it into ſuch diſ-eſteem with others, as it is (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding his ſpecious pretences) with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; who knoweth, that if he could perſwade Chriſtians to think that the <hi>doing it</hi> is never the better, and the <hi>not doing it</hi> never the worſe, it would then ſoon fall to the ground, <hi>J.B. pag.</hi> 104. For the prevention of which deſign, I ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume (through the aſſiſtance of God) to weigh
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:97824:7"/>
what (to the purpoſe) is ſaid (by the Author of the aforeſaid <hi>Treatiſe</hi>) in the ballance of the Sanctuary, if peradventure it may be ſo far outweighed by the weight of Truth, that the vanity thereof may appear.</p>
            <p>Wherein I ſhall firſt take notice of the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of his Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, The <hi>reaſon of his Practice,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Firſt, In his <hi>Confeſſion</hi> you have divers things declared in the beginning thereof (as the <hi>Author</hi> ſaith) which (I ſuppoſe) few men deny; and thereto I ſhall yield my Conceſſion; ſaying to him in the words of the Apoſtle <hi>James,</hi> Chap. 2.19. <hi>Thou ſayeſt well; the Devils alſo believe and tremble.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But when he proceeds further in the 15th <hi>Article</hi> of his Faith, <hi>pag.</hi> 9. wherein he would be thought to be ſome body, in giving a clear demonſtration (as is pretended) how men come to obtain Righteouſneſs, Redemption, and Salvation from the Curſe of the Law,</p>
            <p>He ſaith;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I believe therefore that the Righteouſneſs and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption by which we that believe ſtand juſt before God, as ſaved from the Curſe of the Law, is the Righteouſneſs and Redemption that conſiſts in the perſonal acts and performances of this Child Jeſus, this God-man, the Lord Chriſt; I ſay, in his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal fulfilling the Law for us, to the utmoſt require<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Juſtice of God; by which means he
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:97824:7"/>
became the end of the Law for Righteouſneſs to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one that believeth, ſo finiſhing tranſgreſſion, and making an end of ſin, and making reconciliation for iniquity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> In this <hi>Article</hi> are two things to be conſidered, <hi>viz.</hi> Firſt, what is believed: Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, wherefore it is believed. Firſt, What is believed: The Confeſſor tells us, <hi>That the Righteouſneſs, Redemption, and Salvation from the Curſe of the Law, obtained by Believers, conſiſts in the perſonal acts of Chriſt.</hi> Art. 15. <hi>pag.</hi> 9. But ſure this is not conſonant to the Scriptures of Truth, which declare them to be wrought and accompliſhed by the Sufferings of Chriſt; this <hi>Peter</hi> acknowledgeth, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.11. <hi>For Chriſt alſo hath once ſuffered for Sins.</hi> And if we come to particulars, the truth thereof will appear: For, Firſt, How are we made Righteous? doth not the Apoſtle declare, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.21. <hi>He hath made him to be ſin for us who knew no ſin, that you might be made the Righteouſneſs of God in him.</hi> So that you ſee we obtain Righteouſneſs by Chriſt's be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made Sin; and if you would know how he was made ſin, let the Prophet anſwer, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.6. <hi>The Lord laid on him the iniquity of us all;</hi> as it is written, <hi>He bare our ſins upon his own bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy on the Tree,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.24. and this was his Paſſion, and not his Perſonal act. Secondly, the Redemption of Chriſtians is wrought by the ſhedding the blood of Chriſt, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19. And
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:97824:8"/>
ſure if that was a perſonal act, it muſt be the perſonal act of the Souldier that pierced him, and not of Chriſt himſelf. Thirdly, Salvation from the Curſe of the Law; the Apoſtle de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.13. conſiſted in his being made a Curſe for us; and how that was, the Apoſtle teſtifieth by his hanging on the Tree, <hi>viz.</hi> the Croſs; and that alſo was the ſuffering and not the act of Chriſt, which as it ought to be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed by every Chriſtian, ſo much more he that pretends himſelf a Preacher (who ſhould ſhew himſelf in all things a Workman that needeth not to be aſhamed, rightly dividing the Word of Truth, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.15.) ought to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh between doing and ſuffering, and that more particularly in this matter; for if Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, Redemption, and Salvation had been performed by his perſonal acts, there had then been no need of his Death and Paſſion, the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity whereof is declared by Chriſt himſelf, <hi>Luk.</hi> 24.46. <hi>(Thus it behoved the Chriſt to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer)</hi> and confirmed by the Apoſtle, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.3. that the <hi>Chriſt muſt needs have ſuffered:</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it muſt be concluded that the aforeſaid bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings were not effected by the perſonal acts of Chriſt. And therefore, although the Confeſſor <hi>(J. B. Epiſt.)</hi> preſumeth a candid Chriſtian may judge the root of the matter to be found in him; it may from what hath been ſaid, be feared that
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:97824:8"/>
the root is evil, and then it is eaſie to judge what the branches will be.</p>
            <p>But now in the ſecond place, let us ſee where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the aforeſaid Article is believed, I was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced to conſider it: becauſe he urgeth it ſo emphatically, <hi>I believe therefore,</hi> as if there was ſomething preceding that would demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate the truth thereof: But I have weighed both the precedent and conſequent Articles, with the Scriptures annexed; and I profeſs I know not what he means by <hi>Therefore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Article precedent is, <hi>I believe this very Child is both God and Man, the Chriſt of the Living God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">J. B. Art. <hi>14.</hi> pag. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> And the Scriptures annexed are, <hi>Luke</hi> 2.7, 12. <hi>Matth.</hi> 1.21, 22. But why he ſhould ſay from thence; <hi>I believe therefore,</hi> &amp;c. to me doth not appear.</p>
            <p>This Confeſſor tells us,<note place="margin">J. B's. <hi>Epiſt.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>That above eleven years he hath weighed, pauſed, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined, &amp; pauſed again theſe Doctrines, and that in cold blood.</hi> Surely it demonſtrates his inſtability to be ſo tedious a tract of time (to uſe his own words) in pauſing and weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; I wiſh that may not be true in him accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the words of <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.7. <hi>Ever learning, and never able to come to the knowledge of the Truth:</hi> For hitherto his Judgment and Underſtanding (notwithſtanding his long pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing) ſeems as cold as his blood.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:97824:9"/>
            <p>If any object, <hi>That it is written, Chriſt gave himſelf for us, laid down his life, was obedient to death; all which amount to acts of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. That the ſufferings were all volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary; that he readily condeſcended to obey his Father's Will, wherein we have cauſe to accept the Grace of Chriſt. But, 2. This was no act, <hi>viz.</hi> no Perſonal act of his: There may be a voluntary ſubmiſſion, a free condeſcenſion, even ſo far as we may be ſaid to lay down our lives, to obey God, and yet no perſonal act. Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans are required to obey God in ſufferings; and it is accounted an Obedience to God when we loſe our lives for his ſake; wherefore although I do extol the perſonal acts of Chriſt in the days of his Fleſh, and deſire to reſpect them in their own Sphere; yet I muſt conclude, as aforeſaid, that thoſe bleſſings are not wrought by his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal acts, but by his ſufferings; as it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, <hi>The Captain of our Salvation is made perfect through ſufferings,</hi> Heb. 2.10. Chriſt hath alſo once ſuffered for us, that thereby he might bring us unto God, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.18.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>J.B.</hi> Art. 16. pag. 10. <hi>I do believe that for the compleating of this work, he was always ſinleſs; did alwayes the things that pleaſed God's Juſtice, that every one of his acts, both of doing and ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and riſing again from the dead, was really and infinitely perfect, being done by him as God-man: Wherefore his acts before he died, are called,</hi> the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:97824:9"/>
Righteouſneſs of God, <hi>his blood,</hi> the blood of God; and herein perceive we the love of God in that he laid down his life for us. <hi>The Godhead which gave vertue to all the acts of the humane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, was then in perfect union with it, when he hanged upon the Croſs for our ſins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is the advice of the Holy Ghoſt, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.11. <hi>That if any man ſpeak, he ſhould ſpeak as the Oracles of God:</hi> But ſure this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor's words are more like the Oracles of the Devils, that of old were accuſtomed to be given ſo ambiguous and obſcure, that no body could underſtand them aright, yet they might be wreſted to the underſtanding of any.</p>
            <p>Such is the matter of the aforeſaid <hi>Article,</hi> wherein it is hard to determine what he means; unleſs it is that the Godhead of Chriſt ſuffered death: which although he doth not plainly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, yet he doth imply (if he ſaith any thing); <hi>For</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>every one of his acts of ſuffering was really perfect, being done by him as God-man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I wonder that he (who pretends that he doth <hi>not abuſively preſent to the Reader, any other Doctrine but what he holds,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>J.B's.</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle.</note> 
               <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth, and Preacheth</hi>) ſhould be ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſive to himſelf and Doctrine, as to Preach and Print that which is ſo inconſiſtent with common ſenſe.</p>
            <p>But to proceed; he ſaith, <hi>The Godhead which gave virtue to all the acts of the Humane Nature,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:97824:10"/>
was then in perfect union with it when he hanged upon the Croſs:</hi> Now to be in perfect union, was to be even as that was, <hi>viz.</hi> hanged upon the Croſs, and alſo dead; which ſure the Confeſſor means; for he further urgeth, that therefore his blood was called <hi>the blood of God;</hi> and <hi>hereby perceive we the Love of God, in that he laid down his life for us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if this be his meaning, it is directly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary unto Truth: for <hi>the Godhead that was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual with the Father,</hi> Phil. 2.6. <hi>with whom there is no variableneſs or ſhadow of turning,</hi> Jam. 1.17. <hi>an Eternal Spirit, immortal,</hi> &amp;c. (as it <hi>hath nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fleſh nor bones,</hi> Luk. 24.3.) cannot die, hath no blood to ſhed.</p>
            <p>Death and Immortality are not congruous; and therefore herein this Confeſſor is miſtaken: for the death of Chriſt was only as he was man. And therefore it is ſaid, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.5. <hi>(When he cometh into the World) A body haſt thou prepared me.</hi> If the Godhead could have died, there needed not the preparation of this body of fleſh, but thereby <hi>(being made man)</hi> he became ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to death (which he was not before:) as it is written, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.14, 15. <hi>Foraſmuch as the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren are partakers of fleſh and blood; he alſo him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf likewiſe took part of the ſame; that through death, he might deſtroy him that bad the power of death:</hi> wherefore <hi>he did not aſſume the nature of Angels, but the ſeed of Abraham,</hi> verſ. 16. As it is
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:97824:10"/>
ſaid, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.9. <hi>He was made a little lower than the Angels, for the ſuffering of death:</hi> This alſo our Confeſſor acknowledged, ſaying, (<hi>Art.</hi> 12.) <hi>The great reaſon why Chriſt clothed himſelf with our fleſh and blood, was, that he might be capable of obtaining Redemption, and that was by his Death, even the death of the Manhood;</hi> As the Apoſtle ſaith, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.18. <hi>Being put to death in the fleſh, in the body of his fleſh,</hi> Col. 1.22. And therefore although ſome Scriptures, alledged by the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor, call the blood of Chriſt the blood of God, and God's Life; it muſt not be taken as proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpoken, but in reſpect to that conjunction between the Deity and Humanity; as figurative<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Chriſt is ſaid to be <hi>Hungry, Thirſty, Naked,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.42. when it is properly to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of his People, as himſelf ſaith, <hi>Inaſmuch as ye did it not to the leaſt of theſe, ye did it not to me:</hi> And in this ſenſe God ſaith, <hi>He that touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth you, toucheth the apple of mine eye,</hi> Zech. 2.8. In which ſenſe alſo the aforeſaid Scriptures may well be underſtood, although the Deity is Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal.</p>
            <p>Touching divers other Articles of this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor's Creed, although ſtuffed with many pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe words and incongruities of ſpeech, contrary to that advice, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.13. <hi>Hold faſt the form of ſound words,</hi> I ſhall ſay nothing at this time, but paſs to <hi>Art.</hi> 19. pag. 13. <hi>I believe that the ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings of Chriſt were all voluntary, that he rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:97824:11"/>
condeſcended to obey his Father's Will, wherein we have cauſe to accept the Grace of Chriſt. But</hi> 2. <hi>this was no act,</hi> viz. <hi>no perſonal act of his. There may be a voluntary ſubmiſſion, a free condeſcention, even ſo far as we may be ſaid to lay down our lives to obey God, and yet no perſonal act. Chriſtians are required to obey God in ſuffering, and it is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted an obedience to God when we loſe our lives for his ſake; wherefore although I do extol the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal acts of Chriſt in the dayes of his fleſh, and deſire to reſpect them in their own ſphere, yet muſt conclude, as aforeſaid, that thoſe bleſſings are not wrought by his perſonal acts, but by his ſufferings;</hi> As its written, <hi>The Captain of our Salvation is made perfect through ſufferings,</hi> Heb. 2.10. <hi>Chriſt hath alſo once ſuffered for us, that thereby he might bring us unto God,</hi> 1 Pet. 3.18.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Articles</hi> about <hi>Juſtification, Election,</hi> and <hi>Effectual Calling;</hi> which I ſhall only give you the ſum of what he ſaith, collected (for brevity ſake) out of them all, wherein he declareth That <hi>there is a Decree, Choice, or Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi>
               <note place="margin">J. B. Art. 3. pag. 26. Art. 7. pag. 30.</note> 
               <hi>before the Foundation of the World, even that which contains in it ſelf the Perſons Elected, and the Graces that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company their Salvation, which muſt be wrought in the hearts of ſuch Perſons, there being a neceſſity of the uſe and effect thereof,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Art. 1. pag. 31.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe they are choſen, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they, and they alone are effectually
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:97824:11"/>
called; it being the fruit of Electing love;</hi>
               <note place="margin">pag. 32.</note> 
               <hi>which Call is a word that out-goeth all oppoſition, wherein the Voice of God is heard, the Gates of Heaven are opened;</hi>
               <note place="margin">pag. 33.</note> 
               <hi>there is an effectual awakening of the Soul, in reference to ſin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">pag. 34.</note> 
               <hi>and the World to come; a ſanctifying virtue, whereby Faith, Hope,</hi>
               <note place="margin">pag. 35. pag. 36. pag. 37. pag. 28.</note> 
               <hi>and Repentance are ſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily produced, that there is not any impediment that can hinder their Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and Eternal Salvation; which things are thus effectually wrought only in thoſe which before the World were appointed unto Glory; and the reſt were blinded,</hi>
               <note place="margin">pag. 23. pag. 24. pag. 31.</note> 
               <hi>that as they will not, ſo they cannot hear and turn.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Here you have an account of this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor's Faith, which he ſaith, (in his <hi>Epiſt.) he would have open to the view and judgment of all men:</hi> Wherein (although he is ſo confident, that he makes his appeal even to his Enemies) ſuch unſoundneſs appears, as even ſtrikes at the Juſtice of the God of Heaven, declaring him to be exceeding partial and unequal in his dealings. For I appeal to the World, whether it muſt not be ſo, if <hi>John Bunyan</hi>'s Doctrine aforeſaid (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though eleven years examined) be true.</p>
            <p>If God hath choſen to Salvation before the Foundation of the World any perſons, without any reſpect to qualifications; or if he hath in
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:97824:12"/>
their Election ordained, That they ſhall be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied with ſuch Grace which ſhall of neceſſity produce the Effects intended, and that ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all oppoſition, that there is no impediment can hinder their Converſion and Eternal Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: And again, <hi>Hath blinded others, that they cannot hear, or turn:</hi> What reſpect of perſons, without controule is this? Yea, what iniquity and injuſtice is it which <hi>J. B.</hi> declares? But far be it from our God: <hi>Shall not the Judge of all the Earth do right?</hi> Whom that I may (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to my abilities) vindicate to the world a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>John Bunyan</hi> and his groundleſs Creed, I ſhall firſt endeavour to ſhew his deceipt; Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, I ſhall demonſtrate the righteous deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of our God in behalf of the Salvation of mankind. Wherein conſider theſe things in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to <hi>John Bunyan</hi>'s Creed, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That God doth not Elect any man unto Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, without reſpect to qualifications foreſeen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>That there is not any ſuch Eternal purpoſe of God, which neceſſarily produceth</hi> John Bunyan<hi>'s Effectual Call.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>There is no ſuch Call as is beyond all oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>There is not any ſuch Eſtate as no impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment can hinder the Converſion and Salvation of a man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>There is no Perſon originally ſo far blinded by
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:97824:12"/>
the God of Heaven, that they cannot hear, and turn to him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe things, although Negatives, I ſhall Eſſay to demonſtrate to be (although contrary to <hi>John Bunyan</hi>) conſonant to Truth, by the enſuing Arguments: <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 1. If God Electeth ſome Perſons with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reſpect to qualifications fore-ſeen; Then there is reſpect of Perſons with God: But there is no reſpect of Perſons with God; <hi>Ergo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Major</hi> is undeniable; for if there be no reſpect to qualifications, there muſt be reſpect of perſons, or reſpect to nothing. Peradventure it will be ſaid, that there is reſpect to nothing, it is of God's meer will and pleaſure: whereto I ſhall Anſwer, That if God looking upon every man alike, <hi>viz.</hi> without reſpect to any qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, chooſeth one and not another, it is par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiality; and therefore the <hi>Major</hi> appeareth true.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Minor</hi> is evidently proved, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.11. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.17. and poſitively affirmed, <hi>Acts</hi> 10.34. <hi>I know of a truth</hi> (ſaith <hi>Peter) that God is no reſpecter of perſons:</hi> which afterwards he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrates, <hi>verſ.</hi> 35. <hi>In every Nation, he that feareth God, and worketh Righteouſneſs</hi> (he doth not ſay he that is Elected) <hi>is accepted of him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 2. If God hath from the beginning E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected any perſons to Salvation, without reſpect to qualifications fore-ſeen: Then the Sentence ſhall not paſs at the laſt Day, and Judgment be
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:97824:13"/>
rendred to every man according to their works. But the Sentence at the laſt Day ſhall paſs, and Judgment be rendred to every man according to their works. <hi>Ergo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Major</hi> is plain; for if it ſhall be accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to our works, then not according to ſuch Election; if it be of Election as aforeſaid, then not according to works.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Minor</hi> is confirmed, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.17. <hi>Matth.</hi> 16.27. and <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.6. where it is ſaid, <hi>God will render to every man according to his deeds;</hi> and <hi>verſ.</hi> 7. ſpeaking of Eternal Life, he ſaith, <hi>It ſhall be rendred to them who by patient continuing in well-doing, ſeek for glory, honour, and immortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</hi> Chriſt alſo declares, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.12. <hi>That at his coming he will give to every man</hi> (without excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) <hi>according as his works ſhall be.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 3. If thoſe men that are ſaved, are ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved through Election without reſpect to quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications; Then muſt the reſidue be reprobated without reſpect to qualifications. But God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probates no man without reſpect to qualificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>Ergo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Major</hi> is evident; for if there be a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain number Elected, the reſidue muſt be dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, let their qualifications be what they will: The conſideration whereof, hath induced Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men to blaſpheme, ſaying, <hi>That God ordained men to ſin, that he might juſtly accompliſh his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination;</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:97824:13"/>
So ſaith <hi>Zanchius, Reprobates are held ſo faſt under God's Almighty Decree, that they cannot but ſin and periſh.</hi> And again he ſaith, <hi>There lieth upon Reprobates, by the power of their unchangeable reprobation, a neceſſity of ſinning, yea of ſinning unto death without Repentance; and conſequently of periſhing everlaſtingly,</hi> Zanch. <hi>lib.</hi> 5. <hi>de Nat. Dei.</hi> The ſame alſo ſaith <hi>Piſcator; Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probates are preciſely appointed to ſin, that they might be juſtly puniſhed.</hi> Piſcat. <hi>reſp. ad dupl. vorſt. part.</hi> 1. <hi>pag.</hi> 220.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Maccovius</hi> alſo was of this mind, ſaying, <hi>God did will ſin, ordain men to ſin, that he might juſtly accompliſh his determination.</hi> Macc. <hi>diſp.</hi> 17. <hi>pag.</hi> 11.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee the <hi>Major</hi> is acknowledged by thoſe that believe ſuch an Election as <hi>J. B.</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Minor</hi> I ſhall prove thus, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 4. If God reprobates any man without reſpect to qualifications; Then are not his ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der mercies over all his works. But God's ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der mercies are over all his works. <hi>Ergo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Major</hi> is unqueſtionable; for ſure no mercy (much leſs tender mercy) can be to that man reprobated (and that without reſpect to qualifications) to Eternal damnation.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Minor</hi> is proved, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145.9. <hi>The Lord is good to all</hi> (without exception) <hi>and his ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der mercies are over all his works.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:97824:14"/>This that hath been ſaid, may ſuffice alſo to ſhew, that there is no ſuch Eternal purpoſe, which neceſſarily produceth <hi>John Bunyan</hi>'s Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual Call: For the aforeſaid <hi>Arguments</hi> have the ſame validity againſt that, as the former Propoſition. I come therefore now to ſhew you that there is no ſuch Call as <hi>John Bunyan</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to be beyond all oppoſition. Which I ſhall prove thus: <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 5. If God's Call is oft-times rejected, his Spirit reſiſted, and his Counſel deſpiſed; Then his Call is not beyond all oppoſition: But God's Call is oft-times rejected, his Spirit re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted, and his Counſel deſpiſed. <hi>Ergo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I think I may ſpare the proof of the <hi>Major;</hi> for ſure, unleſs (as <hi>J. B.</hi> ſeems to do) you will ſo diſtinguiſh in this caſe, as if God did not Call thoſe that reject it, with ſuch an intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as he doth others: (as <hi>Piſcator</hi> preſumes to affirm, <hi>That although God commands Reprobates to believe the Goſpel, yet he will not have them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve.</hi> And again, <hi>God doth not offer Grace to thoſe that are Called, with an intent to give it.</hi> And he further ſaith, <hi>Though God in words proteſt that he would have Reprobates believe, yet indeed he will not have them.</hi> Piſcat. <hi>contra. Scaſm. pag.</hi> 60, <hi>pag.</hi> 74, <hi>pag.</hi> 143.) which I hope you will not, leſt you make the God of Heaven as deceitful as the falſe Godds, whom the <hi>Poets</hi> feign, did once ſet <hi>Tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tallus</hi> up to the Chin in a goodly River, under a
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:97824:14"/>
Tree full of beautiful Fruit, which hung even to his Noſe; but ſo, that he could neither reach the fruit, nor ſtoop to the water to drink: which far be it from the Lord, who is true and holy in all his words and actions.</p>
            <p>Wherefore I ſhall proceed to the proof of the <hi>Minor,</hi> which is evident, <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.24. <hi>I have called, but you have refuſed.</hi> Acts 7.51. <hi>Ye have alwayes reſiſted the Holy Spirit, ye have ſet at nought all my Counſel,</hi> Prov. 1.25.</p>
            <p>The next thing I come to, is to ſhew that there are impediments which hinder the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion and Salvation of men; which will thus appear:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 6. If God uſeth ſuch means with the Unconverted as is ſufficient for their Converſion, and yet they continue unconverted; Then ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in themſelves is an impediment: But God uſeth ſuch means with the Unconverted as is ſufficient for their Converſion, and yet they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue unconverted: <hi>Ergo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Major</hi> is true; for if the means be ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, and ſuch means uſed by the God of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, their own obſtinay muſt hinder.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Minor</hi> I prove from the words of Chriſt to <hi>Chorazin</hi> and <hi>Bethſaida,</hi> Matth. 11.21. <hi>If the mighty works which have been done in you, had been done in</hi> Tyre <hi>and</hi> Sidon, <hi>they would have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented long ago.</hi> Now hereby it appeareth, That the means uſed with <hi>Chorazin</hi> and <hi>Bethſaida,</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:97824:15"/>
would have been ſufficient for the Converſion of <hi>Tyre</hi> and <hi>Sidon;</hi> and if ſo, why not to them? Surely becauſe they were more obſtinate. So that we muſt conclude, that was an impediment which did hinder their Converſion, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently their Salvation.</p>
            <p>But further concerning <hi>Salvation,</hi> I offer this:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 7. If the Righteous man may turn from his Righteouſneſs, put away a good Conſcience, and make ſhipwrack of Faith; Then ſomething may impede his Salvation: But a Righteous man may turn from his Righteouſneſs, put away a good Conſcience, and make ſhipwrack of Faith: <hi>Ergo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Major</hi> is undeniable: and the <hi>Minor</hi> I prove, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.24. <hi>When the righteous man turneth from his righteouſneſs, and committeth ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, he ſhall die:</hi> Hymeneus <hi>and</hi> Alexander <hi>put away a good Conſcience, and made ſhipwrack of Faith,</hi> 1 Tim. 1.19. Wherefore alſo <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.27. <hi>I keep under my body, and bring it into ſubjection, leſt that by any means when I have Preached to others, I my ſelf ſhould be a caſt-away.</hi> It ſeems <hi>Paul</hi> was not of <hi>J. B</hi>'s mind, to think that no impediment could hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his Salvation, for then he would not have uſed theſe words, <hi>Leſt that by any means, I my ſelf ſhould be a caſt-away:</hi> But he thought and knew, as it was ſaid of <hi>Eli</hi> to <hi>Samuel,</hi> 1 Sam. 2.30. <hi>They that deſpiſe me, ſhall be lightly eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed;</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:97824:15"/>
As the Lord ſaid by <hi>Oded,</hi> 2 Chron. 15.2. <hi>If ye forſake me, I will forſake you:</hi> Whereof <hi>David</hi> did adviſedly admoniſh <hi>Solomon,</hi> 1 Chron. 28.9. <hi>If thou forſake thy God, he will caſt thee off for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I proceed now to the laſt thing, <hi>viz.</hi> To ſhew you that no Perſons are originally ſo far blinded by the God of Heaven, that they cannot turn to to him: which is thus proved;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 1. If God doth ſo blind any man, Then he is willing that ſome ſhould periſh: But God is not willing that any ſhould periſh: <hi>Ergo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Major</hi> is plain; for God muſt needs be willing to that which himſelf is the cauſe of.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Minor</hi> is proved, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.9. <hi>The Lord is not willing that any ſhould periſh.</hi> He confirms it by an Oath, (which ought to put an end to all ſtrife, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.16.) and becauſe he could ſwear by no greater, he ſwears by himſelf; <hi>As I live, ſaith the Lord</hi> (Ezek. 33.11.) <hi>I have no pleaſure</hi> (at all) <hi>in the death of the wicked, but deſire that he may turn from his ſin and live.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 2. If God doth ſo blind men (<hi>viz.</hi> ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginally); Then their unbelief is no ſin: But the unbelief of any man is ſin: <hi>Ergo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Major</hi> is plain; for if they cannot be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, it is no ſin; our Proverb ſaith, <hi>Neceſſity hath no Law;</hi> and the Scripture ſaith, <hi>Where there is no Law, there is no Tranſgreſſion:</hi> And it
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:97824:16"/>
is true in this caſe, as <hi>John Bunyan</hi> himſelf con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth, <hi>Laws themſelves muſt give place ſometimes for the profit of the Church,</hi> pag. 111. (I will not aſſent to that): But for the proof of the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor,</hi> I ſay, if they muſt give place for the profit of the Church, much more when neceſſity may be pleaded. No King would account that a fault which his Subjects cannot help; which is the caſe with men if they be blinded as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Minor</hi> is clearly proved, <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.9. <hi>The Spirit ſhall convince the World of ſin, becauſe they believe not on me:</hi> It ſeems it is ſuch an apparent ſin, as men themſelves ſhall be convinced there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 3. If God doth originally ſo blind men; Then ſome men ſhall be excuſable at the Day of Judgment: But no man ſhall be excuſable at the Day of Judgment: <hi>Ergo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Major</hi> is undeniable; for what better ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe than to ſay, Lord, thou didſt ſo blind me, that I could not hear, or turn; it was thy own act, O Lord, I could not any wayes help it; I was bound in the fetters of determined blindneſs, to do even contrary to mine own will, that thy deſtiny might be accompliſhed, (this <hi>Calvin</hi> ſaith, <hi>The Reprobate are not only held faſt in God's fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, ſo as they cannot do as thy would, but are alſo urged and forced by God's bridle to do as he would have them.</hi> And again, <hi>That Men have nothing
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:97824:16"/>
in agitation, that they bring nothing into action, but what God by his ſecret direction hath ordered,</hi> Calv. Inſtit. lib. 1. chap. 17. ſect. 11. Chap. 18. ſect. 1.) Wherefore, O Lord, how could I avoid my im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitency and incredulity! and wilt thou puniſh me for that which I could not help; even for that which is the effect of thy Almighty Decree! that, Lord, be far from thee, who haſt declared, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.31. <hi>That thou wilt judge the World in Righteouſneſs.</hi> This ſurely would be a ſufficient excuſe.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Minor</hi> is proved, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.1. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.19. <hi>Every mouth ſhall be ſtopped: Thou art inexcuſable whoſoever thou art that judgeſt.</hi> The truth where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of will hereafter (through God's aſſiſtance) be more abundantly demonſtrated.</p>
            <p>Thus the Error of <hi>John Bunyan</hi>'s Faith is diſcovered, and that the contrary may further appear, I come now to ſhew you, in vindicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our God, his righteous dealings with man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind.</p>
            <p>Wherein touching <hi>Election,</hi> know, That God hath, from before the Foundation of the World, choſen ſome in Chriſt Jeſus to Eternal Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; but not without reſpect to qualifications: For, though no qualification of ours was the efficient cauſe of our Election, yet God having teſtified his good pleaſure concerning Man, in Chriſt Jeſus, whoſe Sacrifice he was pleaſed graciouſly to accept, as a Propitiation for our
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:97824:17"/>
ſins; in him he is pleaſed alſo to declare his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation of all thoſe who ſhall obey his will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared in Chriſt Jeſus; not as any thing merited by us, but the effect of his everlaſting kindneſs, wherein he was pleaſed to chuſe unto Salvation all thoſe whom he foreſaw to continue obedient to his holy Will; according to what is ſaid, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.29. <hi>Whom he did fore-know, he alſo did Predeſtinate,</hi> &amp;c. determining that the reſt ſhould be damned, becauſe of their diſobedience, in not hearkning to his Counſel, and not ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to his holy Deſires; which are fruſtrated through their obſtinacy, thereby <hi>treaſuring up to themſelves wrath againſt the day of wrath,</hi> Rom. 2.4. contrary to the good pleaſure of God, who endeavoured earneſtly their Salvation. Now this <hi>Election</hi> is warranted by the Scriptures, as 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.2. <hi>Elect according to the fore-knowledge of God the Father, through Sanctification of the Spirit.</hi> Now what is the Sanctification of the Spirit; but when the heart being enlightned by the Spirit of God, is induced to accept of Grace offered, and to walk ſuitable thereto? And this being fore-ſeen, the Apoſtle declares our Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to be according to the fore-knowledge of God, in reſpect of thoſe qualifications conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered; As <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.13. <hi>God hath from the beginning choſen you to Salvation, through Sanctification of the Spirit, and belief of the Truth.</hi> Now that cannot be without reſpect to quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:97824:17"/>
which you ſee is through ſuch apparent qualifications, as is further plainly demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, in the conſiderations of the dealings of God with men in general; wherein I ſhall ſhew you how God invites every man to obey his Will, that they may be ſaved; yea, ſtrives with them to bring them to Repentance, and alſo waiteth long in expectation of the effects of the power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful working of his Holy Spirit in their hearts; promiſing Salvation according to his everlaſting purpoſe, to all thoſe that obey him, and threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning damnation (although with much lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation) to thoſe that obſtinately deſpiſe him: which ſure muſt needs be inconſiſtent with ſuch an abſolute Election as is pretended by <hi>John Bunyan;</hi> Which therefore I ſhall proceed to do in order; Firſt, ſhewing you the invitations of God: there is no Prophet ſilent therein, he calls by <hi>Ezekiel, Chap.</hi> 18.30. <hi>Repent, and turn from all your tranſgreſſions; ſo iniquity ſhall not be your ruine.</hi> As if he ſhould ſay, Be not miſtaken in your ſelves, neither do ye miſtake me, as to think I have determined your deſtruction: for if you repent, you ſhall live. Wherefore it is added, <hi>verſ.</hi> 31. <hi>Caſt away all your tranſgreſſions,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>for why will you die, O Houſe of Iſrael?</hi> God doth frequently call upon ſinners; yea, <hi>riſing up be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, and ſending, to procure their Repentance, becauſe he hath compaſſion upon them,</hi> 2 Chron. 36.15. As <hi>Jeremiah</hi> witneſſeth, <hi>Jer.</hi> 25.4. <hi>The Lord
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:97824:18"/>
ſent unto you all his Servants the Prophets, riſing early and ſending, ſaying, Turn ye every one from his evil way, and from the evil of his doings.</hi> Now to what purpoſe was all this, if God had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined either their ſin or their damnation? But hear what <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.20. <hi>Wiſdom crieth without, ſhe uttereth her voice in the ſtreets, ſhe crieth in the chief place of concourſe, in the openings of the Gates; in the City ſhe uttereth her words, ſaying, How long, ye ſimple ones, will ye love ſimplicity, and Scorners delight in their ſcourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and Fools hate knowledge? turn you at my reproof: behold, I will pour out my Spirit upon you; I will make known my words unto you:</hi> As it is further declared, <hi>Chap.</hi> 8.1. <hi>Doth not Wiſdom cry, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding put forth her voice?</hi> It is anſwered, <hi>verſ.</hi> 2. <hi>She ſtandeth in the top of the high places; ſhe crieth at the Gates, at the entry of the City, at the coming in of the Doors: <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto you, O men, I call, and my voice is to the Sons of men; O ye Simple, underſtand Wiſdom, and ye Fools be ye of an underſtanding heart.</hi> Conſider the gracious and general invitations of the God of Heaven; he calleth and inviteth men to the obedience of his holy Will; yea, even the worſt of men, Fools, Simple ones, and Scorners; and not only ſuch who were ſo originally, but even thoſe who continued ſo; as appears <hi>Chap.</hi> 1. <hi>verſ.</hi> 24. <hi>Becauſe I called, and you did not anſwer; therefore ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction come upon you as a whirlewind.</hi> Yet theſe
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:97824:18"/>
perſons did the Lord invite, perſwading them by the motives of Grace, and intreating them by familiar expreſſions of kindneſs, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.20. <hi>We then are Embaſſadours for Chriſt, as though God did beſeech you by us; We pray you in Chriſt's ſtead, be ye reconciled unto God.</hi> What expreſſions of mercy are here! was ever the like Grace heard of! which is again found in that text ſo full of love, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.1. <hi>Ho, every one that thirſteth; Come ye to the Waters, Come freely; he that hath no money, come buy and eat; yea, come buy Wine and Milk without money and without price.</hi> (O great Grace!) <hi>Wherefore</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>do ye ſpend money for that which is not bread? Hearken diligently unto me; incline your ear, and hear: and come unto me, and your Soul ſhall live:</hi> What promiſes and gracious in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitations are here! (Is this conſiſtent with God's blinding of men? Is it likely that the only wiſe God ſhould ſpeak thus to ſuch as he knows cannot hear or turn? ſurely nay). Chriſt himſelf calls, <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.28. <hi>Come unto me all ye that labour, and are heavy laden, and I will give you reſt.</hi> Not only ſo, but God alſo ſtrives with wicked men (and that very forcibly) to bring them to Repentance; As it is written, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.21. <hi>All the day long have I ſtretched forth my hand</hi> (even) <hi>to a diſobedient and gain-ſaying People.</hi> Now what is it for God to ſtretch forth his hand? Is it becauſe God hath hands as we
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:97824:19"/>
have? No: but the hand of God is taken in Scripture ſometimes for the Power of God, as <hi>Exod.</hi> 3.20. <hi>I will ſtretch forth my hand and ſmite Egypt:</hi> Yea, ſometimes it is taken for his Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, as <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.14. <hi>The hand of the Lord ſhall be towards his People.</hi> So that for God to ſtretch forth his hand to the wicked, is to ſtrive with them by his Power, and manifeſtation of Grace. Thus God ſtrove with back-ſliding <hi>Ephrahim, Hoſ.</hi> 11.3. <hi>I taught Ephraim to go, I drew them with the cords of a man, with the bands of love; and I was to them as they that take off the yoke on their jaws; and I laid meat unto them.</hi> What expreſſions of love are theſe! I am not able fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>they to illuſtrate them; none knoweth better this Declaration of the dealings of God, than a tender Nurſe, who taketh great care of her little Babes, and uſeth great pains with them: Even ſo doth the Lord with Sinners; yea with All, as Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Joh.</hi> 12.32. <hi>And I, if I be lifted up from the Earth, will draw all men unto me.</hi> Chriſt draweth; the Father draweth; he ſtrives earneſtly with men by his holy Spirit; which being reſiſted, he ſaith, <hi>My Spirit ſhall not alwayes ſtrive with man,</hi> Gen. 6.3. What ſhall we ſay to this? Did the Spirit of God ſtrive with theſe Rebellious men (who died in their iniquity) or did it not? If you ſay it did, then is the truth of the matter granted, and God's Grace to damned perſons acknowledged;
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:97824:19"/>
but if you will ſay it did not, what meaneth then this ſpeech, <hi>My Spirit ſhall not alwayes ſtrive?</hi> Surely therefore we may conclude, there was a time when God did ſtrive with them by his Spirit; yea, by the ſame powerful Spirit that raiſed Chriſt from the dead; As it is written, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.18, 19. <hi>Quickned by the Spirit; by which alſo he went and preached to the Spirits now in Priſon, which were ſometime diſobedient in the dayes of</hi> Noah <hi>while the Ark was preparing.</hi> What is it for Chriſt to preach by his Spirit, but by the operation of his Spirit, to enlighten, and convince the Sons of men: This he did to the old World, and this he doth to every man, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.9. <hi>Chriſt is the true Light, which lighteth every man that cometh into the World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> But peradventure you will ſay, <hi>If God dealeth thus graciouſly, what is the reaſon men con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in diſobedience?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Not becauſe God doth ſo blind them that they cannot hear and turn (as <hi>Joh. Bunyan</hi> ſaith) nor becauſe God doth not work power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully in their hearts; yea, ſo powerfully as to afford them, ſufficient means to obey his Will, (as <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaith, <hi>Deut.</hi> 30.14. <hi>The Word is nigh thee, in thy mouth, and in thy heart, that thou mayeſt do it)?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> But if then you further ark the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I ſay, It is through their own obſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:97824:20"/>
and perverſneſs, whereby they do deſpite to the Spirit of Grace, as it is ſaid, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.4. <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſeſt thou the riches of his Grace, not regarding the goodneſs of God that leadeth thee to Repentance; but after thy hardneſs, and impenitent heart, thou treaſureſt up to thy ſelf wrath againſt the day of Wrath.</hi> God leads to Repentance, but his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is deſpiſed; Man through the hardneſs of his heart, treaſureth up wrath againſt himſelf; reſiſting the motions of God's Spirit; as <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen</hi> ſaid, <hi>Acts</hi> 7.51. <hi>Ye have alwayes reſiſted the Holy Ghoſt, as did your Fathers, ſo do ye:</hi> As it is witneſſed by that pitiful complaint of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.37. <hi>How often would I have ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered thy Children together, as a Hen gathereth her Chickens under her wings, but ye would not?</hi> This obſtinacy of man is the cauſe of his ruine, God ſent his Prophets, but they would not hear, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 24.19. <hi>They pulled away the ſhoulder, ſtopped their ears, and made their hearts hard as an Adamant ſtone, leſt they ſhould hear the words which the Lord ſent in his Spirit by his Prophets, Zech.</hi> 7.12. And therefore wicked men are charged with <hi>doing deſpite to the Spirit of Grace, Heb.</hi> 10.29. So that in truth it is wilful and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate diſobedience that men are guilty of in not hearkning to the Lord.</p>
            <p>God would have them obey his voice, but they will not; yet to manifeſt his Grace he waits abundantly for the Effects of the operation of
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:97824:20"/>
his holy Spirit, and giveth ſpace of Repentance, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.21. that ſo he might win them to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf by his long-ſuffering; and therefore <hi>be waits that he may be gracious,</hi> Iſa. 30.18. by his long-ſuffering, <hi>leading Sinners to Repentance, Rom.</hi> 2.4. as <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, <hi>The Lord is long ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, not willing that any ſhould periſh,</hi> 2 Pet. 3.9. <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ing till there is no remedy,</hi> 2 Chron. 36.16. Which we have evidently deſcribed by a Simile, <hi>Jer.</hi> 6.29. <hi>The Bellows are burnt, the Lead is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed in the fire, the Founder melteth in vain, for the wicked are not plucked away.</hi> The Lord here alludes to a Refiner, who taketh great pains in the Refining a Maſs of Silver; and exerciſeth ſuch patience, as to wait till the Lead (which Refiners uſe to put in for the better purifying the Silver) is conſumed, and (through the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity of heat) the Bellows burnt; ſo that all his labour is (more then) in vain: (thus God deals with men) whereof he complains, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.4. <hi>I have laboured in vain, I have ſpent my ſtrength for nought, and in vain:</hi> Inſomuch that (in juſtification of himſelf againſt <hi>John Bunyan</hi> and ſuch others) he appeals to his Enemies in the caſe, <hi>viz. Judge, I pray you, what could I have done more for Sinners than I have done?</hi> Iſa. 5.4. I have given my Son to redeem them from death, and in him I have alſo offered them E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Salvation, which I have invited them to imbrace; and alſo endeavoured to effect in their
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:97824:21"/>
hearts, by the motions of my holy Spirit, for the operation whereof I have waited, even un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til I perceived all my endeavours to be in vain; my Spirit is reſiſted, and in deſpite thereof they have perſiſted in wickedneſs, wherein what could I have done more, or what can I now do? ſave only bewail their folly, in that they ſhould ſo (againſt my will) <hi>forſake their own mer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4+ letters">
                     <desc>••••…</desc>
                  </gap> Jona</hi> 2.8. and that alſo the Lord frequently doth; he grieveth for the deſtruction of Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, <hi>Jer.</hi> 4.19. <hi>My bowels, my bowels; I am pained at my very heart:</hi> Not that God hath Bowels or an Heart like men, but the bowels of the Father are his tender mercies, and great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, being unwilling to puniſh; <hi>For the Lord doth not afflict willingly, nor grieve the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Men,</hi> Lam. 3.33. It is hard with the Lord (<hi>viz.</hi> againſt his good pleaſure) <hi>How</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſhall I give thee up</hi> (O backſliding) <hi>Ephraim? How ſhall I deliver thee</hi> (to death) (O ſinful) <hi>Iſrael? How ſhall I make thee as Adama? How ſhall I ſet thee as Zeboim? My heart is turned within me, my repentings are kindled toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> Hoſ. 11.8. Thus the Son of God, being like unto his Father in compaſſion, when he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> Luk. 19.41, 42. he wept over it, becauſe they would not know the things that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to their peace; he was grieved for the hardneſs of their hearts, <hi>Mark</hi> 3.5. wiſhing it had been otherwiſe; <hi>O that thou hadſt hearkned
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:97824:21"/>
to my Commandments,</hi> Iſa. 48.18. <hi>O that Iſrael had walked in my wayes,</hi> Pſa. 81.16. What great compaſſion is this? what demonſtrations of love are here? When Jeſus wept for <hi>Lazarus,</hi> Joh. 11.35. The <hi>Jews</hi> looked upon it as a great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration of love: and is it not ſo in God to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Sinners? When <hi>David</hi> wept after <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi>'s Bier, and bewailed him, it is ſaid, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.37. That <hi>all Iſrael underſtood that day, that the death of</hi> Abner <hi>was not of the King;</hi> but far con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to his mind: And ſurely alſo we may conclude (from what hath been alleaged) that the death of Sinners is not of our God, he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver determined any ſuch thing; neither is he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ways the cauſe thereof, it is far from him; whereby, as we may perceive the death of Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners is altogether of themſelves, and not by or through God's blinding them. So the order of his Election may be perceived contrary to <hi>John Bunyan</hi>'s Faith; the <hi>Confeſſion</hi> whereof I have now done with: (having offered thus much, becauſe that God is much diſhonoured, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny People deceived through the not underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding theſe things); I come now to the <hi>Reaſon</hi> of his <hi>Practice in Worſhip.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>J.B. pag.</hi> 48. Wherein he firſt diſtinguiſheth between thoſe <hi>with whom he dares not have Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion,</hi> and <hi>thoſe with whom he dares (have Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with,</hi> I ſuppoſe he means.)</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:97824:22"/>Concerning what he ſaith touching thoſe <hi>with whom he dare not have Communion,</hi> I ſhall leave him unto himſelf; only take notice, That thoſe who do not profeſs Faith and Holineſs, yea, the open Prophane, may be nearer Heaven than thoſe that pretend great Zeal without Knowledge. Our Saviour ſaid of old, <hi>Matth.</hi> 21.31. <hi>That the Publicans and Harlots enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Kingdom of God before you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I ſhall now conſider what <hi>J. B.</hi> ſaith <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning whom he dare;</hi> which he thus declares, <hi>I dare have Communion,</hi> yea, <hi>Church-Communion with thoſe that are viſible Saints by calling; with thoſe that by the Word of the Goſpel have been brought over to Faith and Holineſs.</hi> pag. 65. <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though</hi> (as afterwards he declares, as well as in his Title Page) <hi>they diſſent about Water-Baptiſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If <hi>J. Bunyan</hi> had only ſaid this, I know not who would have gainſaid; nay, if he had told us, that he could have Communion with the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> I know not who would have oppoſed him, except the Catholicks themſelves, who peradventure (conſidering the Errors of his Faith) would not judge him fit for Communion with them.</p>
            <p>But <hi>John Bunyan</hi> proceeds to perſwade others to do the ſame, and therefore he urgeth great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the reaſon of his Practice, to draw Diſciples after him. I wiſh the event be not as Chriſt ſaid to the Phariſees, <hi>Matt.</hi> 23.15. <hi>Ye compaſs Sea
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:97824:22"/>
and Land to make one Proſelyte, and when he is made, ye make him twofold more the Child of Hell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But before we judge, let us hear him ſpeak, let us weigh what is ſaid therein; I readily perceive he hath learned what <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.17. That <hi>in vain is the Net ſpread in the ſight of any Bird:</hi> Wherefore by crafty inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and ſubtile evaſions, he endeavoureth to darken Counſel, the better to undermine the hearts of the weak, that his deceit might not be diſcovered.</p>
            <p>Wherefore not ſuddenly coming to the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, he endeavoureth by fair pretences (although mixt with tautologies and incongruous relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) to pre-engage the <hi>Reader.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> And then (at length) propounds this queſtion, <hi>pag.</hi> 70. <hi>By what rule would you receive him into Fellowſhip?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which he <hi>anſwers</hi> himſelf thus; <hi>Even by a diſcovery of their Faith and Holineſs, and their declaration of willingneſs to ſubject themſelves to the Laws and Government of Chriſt in his Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> This anſwer being given, he offers a ſecond queſtion, <hi>viz. But do you not count that by Water-Baptiſm, and not otherwiſe, that being the initiating and entring Ordinance, they ought to be received into Fellowſhip?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this he preſumes to anſwer, <hi>No:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If I underſtand this anſwer, it denies
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:97824:23"/>
Baptiſm to be a diſcovery of Faith and Holineſs, or a declaration of willingneſs to ſubject to the Laws of Chriſt in his Church; for the Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is, <hi>Do you not count that by Water-baptiſm,</hi> &amp;c. which muſt have reſpect to the former deſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his Rule, wherein (it ſeems) Water-Baptiſm hath now no part, and in truth it muſt be ſo excluded (by <hi>J. Bunyan</hi>'s opinion) for otherwiſe that (in deſpight of what he hath ſaid) would be the Rule propoſed by himſelf.</p>
            <p>But herein hath not <hi>John Bunyan</hi> forgot him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf? <hi>Pag.</hi> 64. he <hi>acknowledgeth Water-baptiſm to be an Ordinance of Chriſt, a holy Ordinance, a duty enjoyned to ſuch as have received the Goſpel before, yet now he denies it to be a diſcovery of Faith and Holineſs, or a declaration of willingneſs to ſubject to the Laws of Chriſt in his Church.</hi> pag. 122, 123.</p>
            <p>What impudent Contradictions are here! an Ordinance of Chriſt, an holy Ordinance, a du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty enjoyned to Goſpel-Receivers, and yet no diſcovery of Faith, <hi>Is not Faith diſcovered by Works?</hi> Jam. 2.17. And by what works, if not obedience to Chriſt's Ordinances, to holy Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, to enjoyned duties, I know not, ſurely? what, if not this, diſcovers Faith?</p>
            <p>Again, an Ordinance of Chriſt, an holy Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, a Duty enjoyned, and yet no diſcovery of Holineſs? Is it not Holineſs it ſelf to obey Chriſt's Ordinances; his holy Ordinances; to perform duties enjoyned? Thus <hi>the wiſe are ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:97824:23"/>
in their own craftineſs;</hi> 1 Cor. 3.19.</p>
            <p>Further, Is not a real ſubjection to Chriſt's Ordinances, a real performance of thoſe Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties enjoyned us, the beſt declaration of a wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingneſs thereto? yet all this <hi>John Bunyan</hi> is pleaſed poſitively to deny; although he doth not only confeſs concerning Baptiſm as aforeſaid, <hi>viz. That it is an Ordinance of Chriſt, an holy Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, a Duty enjoyned:</hi> But further tells us, <hi>It is of excellent uſe to the Church.</hi> pag. 64.</p>
            <p>But what is that? It ſeems it is no diſcovery of Faith, nor Holineſs, nor a willingneſs to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to Chriſt's Laws (it is of no uſe in theſe things) nor of any uſe in Church-Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, what excellent uſe is it then of?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>John Bunyan</hi> anſwers; <hi>It is a repreſentation of the Death and Reſurrection of Chriſt; an help to our Faith; yea, meet to inſtruct us in the moſt weighty matters of the Kingdom of God,</hi> pag. 64, 65.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> Well ſaid, <hi>John Bunyan!</hi> it ſeems now Baptiſm is good for ſomething; the Devils ſometimes were enforced to confeſs Chriſt, (ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Mark</hi> 3.11. <hi>Luk.</hi> 4.34, 41. <hi>We know thee who thou art, Jeſus the Holy One of God</hi>) al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they were his great Enemies: Even ſo <hi>J. B.</hi> is (in this) inconſiſtent (not only to Truth, but alſo) to himſelf; for ſure the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to ſuch an Ordinance as is ordained by Chriſt; a repreſentation of his Death and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:97824:24"/>
a help to our Faith, an inſtruction in the moſt weighty matters of the Kingdom of God, an enjoyned Duty; is a diſcovery of Faith and Holineſs, and a declaration of ſubjection to Chriſt's Laws.</p>
            <p>And if ſo, then it is the Rule of Communion <hi>John Bunyan</hi> himſelf propoſeth in his afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned deſcription, <hi>pag.</hi> 70. and ſo the cauſe he hath wilfully loſt: but no marvel that men are deceived, when they ſtand up againſt the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>But tarry; <hi>We muſt not conclude,</hi> he ſaith, <hi>Baptiſm is no initiating or entring Ordinance into Church-Communion; and herein is the miſtake, to think it is ſo; becauſe in time paſt Baptiſm was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred upon converſion.</hi> pag. 70.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If by <hi>time paſt,</hi> he meaneth the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle's dayes (which I preſume he doth: for he further confeſſeth that Water-baptiſm in the Primitive times was generally ſubmitted to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Church-Communion, <hi>pag.</hi> 91, 92.)</p>
            <p>I wonder where is the greateſt miſtake, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in <hi>John Bunyan</hi>'s vilifying the Ordinances of Baptiſm; or in the obſervation thereof (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording (as himſelf confeſſeth) the Practice of the Primitive Church; and that upon Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion before Communion? ſure there can be no miſtake in following ſo good a pattern.</p>
            <p>But he proceeds to tell us, <hi>The Word doth not teſtifie it to be an initiating Ordinance.</hi> pag. 70.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:97824:24"/>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> What teſtimony need we have further than your own Confeſſion, <hi>(out of thy own mouth thou ſhalt be judged);</hi> Is not the Primitive pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern, their general Practice, a ſufficient teſtimony? Doth not the word of the Scripture enjoyn us to follow that Example? But peradventure <hi>J. B.</hi> would have a plain Text to ſay Baptiſm is an initiating Ordinance: wherein I commend <hi>John Bunyan</hi> in putting the queſtion into ſuch terms, as he well knew were not to be found ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly in the Scripture: he thought it would make moſt for his advantage, and might carry the beſt gloſs in the denial; which to illuſtrate, he tells you, <hi>pag.</hi> 71. <hi>It wants the nature and power of ſuch an Ordinance; for that which is the initiating Ordinance</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>doth give to the partakers a being of Church-memberſhip in that particular Church, by which it is adminiſtred, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the addition of another Church-act;</hi> And this he endeavoureth to prove by the Example of Circumciſion, <hi>which</hi> (ſaith he, <hi>pag.</hi> 71.) <hi>was to the</hi> Jews <hi>an initiating Ordinance, whereby they were made forthwith Church-members; and alſo none ſo accompted, nor admitted, but thoſe that did partake thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> His proofs for what is here ſaid are va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, although when enquired into, there is no ſuch thing to be found, and therefore I may ſay it is a deceipt of <hi>J. B;</hi> for (as he ſaith of Baptiſm, ſo muſt I ſay of Circumciſion) by
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:97824:25"/>
the Word there is no ſuch thing to be found. Where is Circumciſion called expreſly in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, an initiating Ordinance? yet <hi>J. B.</hi> is pleaſed ſo to call it; upon far leſs grounds than there is for Baptiſm ſo to be called: for if Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion was ſuch an Ordinance as he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes, what muſt be ſaid of <hi>Sarai, Rebeka, Deborah,</hi> and all the holy Women of old, who at once <hi>John Bunyan</hi> ſhuts the Church-door a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, and will not ſuffer them to enter.</p>
            <p>It is well God's thoughts are not like mens. Surely I might upon better grounds than <hi>J. B.</hi> prove, That ſome uncircumciſed perſons were admitted to Church-fellowſhip. For if uncircum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed perſons were admitted into the Temple of God to pray there, &amp;c. Then uncircumciſed per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons were Church-Members; for the Temple was more peculiar, than the Paſſeover: But <hi>Anna,</hi> and divers Holy Women (uncircumciſed perſons) did reſide in the Temple. <hi>Ergo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea further; if I ſhould ſay, Holy Women did eat the Paſſeover, I ſuppoſe I ſhould not be gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid: although it overthrows <hi>John Bunyan</hi>'s po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition: but we ſee this, like the <hi>Sodomites,</hi> that whilſt they endeavoured to break open the door of <hi>Lot</hi>'s houſe, they were ſo ſmitten with blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that they could not find the doors of their own, <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.11. this aſtoniſhed them. But <hi>John Bunyan</hi> is more obdurate, for he yet perſiſts in the defamation of Baptiſm, and tells us, <hi>p.</hi> 74.
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:97824:25"/>
Firſt, <hi>There was none debarred or threatned to be cut off from the Church, if not firſt baptized, Secondly, That Baptiſm doth not give a being of Memberſhip in this or that particular Church, by whoſe Members the Parties are baptized.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Firſt, how can <hi>J. Bunyan</hi> expect any inſtance to be given of the debarring of any un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptized Perſon, when that (by his own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, <hi>pag.</hi> 91.) in the Primitive times they were (generally even all Diſciples) baptized upon Converſion? And if ſo, much leſs can it be expected to find any threatned to be cut off from the Church, becauſe not firſt baptized, there not being in thoſe dayes ſuch an Heretick hatch'd as would ſo explode Baptiſm.</p>
            <p>To the ſecond, <hi>That Baptiſm doth not give a being of Memberſhip into this or that particular Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer, It is not required, if conſidered di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly, neither did Circumciſion ſo; although much boaſted of. Did Circumciſion give a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Memberſhip in particular Churches di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct; one Perſon to be a member at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> another at <hi>Capernaum,</hi> &amp;c. and there only? No ſurely; he that was a member in one place, was a member in all; and therefore <hi>J. Bunyan</hi>'s needleſs queſtions and aſſertions, <hi>pag.</hi> 74. might have been ſpared; for the <hi>Eunuch, Cornelius, Lydia,</hi> the <hi>Samaritans, &amp;c.</hi> were accepted as Church-members in general, and ſo of every
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:97824:26"/>
Church in particular, and that even upon their Baptiſm, although this Anti-Baptiſm would have you believe that in the ſecond of the <hi>Acts,</hi> Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, and adding to the Church, appear to be two diſtinct things; whom I would have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member <hi>Solomon</hi> his advice, <hi>Prov.</hi> 30.6. <hi>Add thou not to his words, leſt he reprove thee, and thou be found a lyar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>John Bunyan</hi> is now grown poſitive, and confidently ſaith, <hi>pag.</hi> 76. <hi>Take it again; Baptiſm makes thee no member of the Church, neither par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular nor univerſal: neither doth it make thee a viſible Saint: It therefore gives thee neither right to, nor being of Memberſhip at all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Here is a brave flouriſh; but an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent aſſertion, contrary to truth: but no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel that you find him contrary to truth, who is contrary to almoſt all Chriſtians, yea to himſelf, and that often in one little Book. Wherefore, although he excludes Baptiſm ſo utterly, as to ſay it doth not make us members at all; yet I ſhall affirm that Baptiſm in a ſenſe (yea, in a great meaſure) doth make us Church-members, which alſo <hi>J. Bunyan</hi> doth confeſs, and that from the Example of the Primitive Saints: For he acknowledgeth, <hi>pag.</hi> 70. <hi>That in the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive times Baptiſm was adminiſtred upon Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion;</hi> yea, he further grants, <hi>pag.</hi> 91. <hi>That in the Apoſtles dayes Water-Baptiſm went before Church-Memberſhip.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:97824:26"/>Now that which was adminiſtred upon the Converſion of Perſons; yea, before they were Church-members, and thereupon to be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Church-members, (which <hi>John Bunyan</hi> in his right mind is forced to acknowledge of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm); ſure muſt be ſaid in a great meaſure to make us Church-members; and Baptiſm being ſo adminiſtred in the Primitive times, is it not neceſſary it ſhould be ſo now? Can we alter the Primitive manner of receiving into the Church, without being guilty of great iniquity? ought we not to follow the Examples of the Primitive Churches?</p>
            <p>Since I have proceeded thus far, having now the appearance of ſo good grounds, I ſhall (through God's aſſiſtance) adventure to prove the neceſſity thereof, (not being at all affrighted with <hi>J. Bunyan</hi>'s opprobrious cenſures), where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in if I ſhould affirm Baptiſm to be an initiating Ordinance, it would appear to be true by <hi>John Bunyan</hi>'s own Confeſſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 1. For that which ought to be admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred upon Converſion, before Church-member<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, is an initiating Ordinance: But Baptiſm ought to be adminiſtred before Church-member<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip upon Converſion: <hi>Ergo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Major</hi> I ſuppoſe none will deny; the <hi>Minor</hi> I prove thus:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 2. If Baptiſm was ſo adminiſtred in the Primitive Churches; Then it ought to be ſo
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:97824:27"/>
now: But Baptiſm was ſo adminiſtred in the Primitive Churches: <hi>Ergo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Minor</hi> is <hi>J. Bunyan</hi>'s own grant, <hi>pag.</hi> 70. <hi>pag.</hi> 91. The <hi>Major</hi> is proved, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.1. where the Apoſtle beſeecheth and exhorteth, and that by the Lord Jeſus, That <hi>Saints ſhould walk as we have received from them;</hi> yea, in 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3.6. he commands the Churches in the Name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>to with-draw from every one that walketh ſo diſorderly;</hi> viz. not according to the Traditions of the Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>Again; Is not Baptiſm called (<hi>Heb.</hi> 5.12. &amp; <hi>Chap.</hi> 6.1, 2.) one of the firſt Principles of the Oracles of God, a Principle of the Doctrine of Chriſt, part of the Foundation? and what is that but an initiating or entring Ordinance? Is not the laying the foundation of an houſe a great entrance to the building? So is Baptiſm in the practice of Chriſtianity? And are not the firſt Principles in any Matter or Doctrine, the initiating or entring thereinto? The ſame is Baptiſm, as aforeſaid, in Chriſtianity. I might evidently ſet forth that it may truly be ſo called: but leaving that denomination, I ſhall (touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Controverſie in hand) ſtate this Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That Baptiſm is a duty neceſſarily to be obſerved by Chriſtians in obedience to God, and in order to Church-Communion:</hi> I ſay, neceſſarily to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved; for ſome things are lawful for a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:97824:27"/>
but not expedient: Some things again are expedient, but not neceſſary; but other things are neceſſary and muſt be done, of which ſort is Baptiſm. This Chriſt himſelf teſtifieth, <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.15. <hi>Thus it behooveth us,</hi> (mark) he ſpeaketh not particularly of himſelf, but alſo of his followers, <hi>us:</hi> And alſo he ſaith, Thus it behoveth, <hi>Oportet nos:</hi> we muſt do thus to fulfil God's righteous Commands. When <hi>Paul</hi> was miraculouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, he was Commanded by the Lord, to go into the City, and there it ſhould be told him what he muſt do, <hi>Acts</hi> 9.6. and what that was appears from the words of <hi>Ananias,</hi> rehearſed by <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf, <hi>Acts</hi> 22.16. <hi>Ariſe and be baptized;</hi> This <hi>Peter</hi> ſheweth the neceſſity of, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.21. by a figurative demonſtration, ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the <hi>Ark</hi> of <hi>Noah, Wherein few (that is eight Souls) were ſaved by Water: The like figure whereunto,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>Baptiſm, doth alſo now ſave us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Surely, the Ark was ſo neceſſary for their Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation (<hi>viz.</hi> their preſervation from death) that only they that were therein were ſaved; and the Apoſtle tells you Baptiſm is the like: <hi>but</hi> (as he afterwards explains) <hi>not the putting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the filth of the fleſh, but the anſwer of a good Conſcience towards God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now how neceſſary a good Conſcience is, and how much to be preſſed after, I think I need not tell you; and Baptiſm is the anſwer of a good
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:97824:28"/>
Conſcience towards God, it is ſo venerable an Ordinance (notwithſtanding <hi>John Bunyan</hi> is pleaſed to ſlight it, ſaying, <hi>pag.</hi> 104. <hi>We are not the better if we do it, or the worſe if we do it not: not the better</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>before God, nor the worſe before men</hi>). That thoſe who are ſubject there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, are ſaid, <hi>Luk.</hi> 7.29. <hi>to juſtifie God,</hi> (what greater applauſe can men have) and on the contrary thoſe that do not ſubmit thereto, <hi>reject the Counſel of God againſt themſelves:</hi> and muſt not this be concluded to be a neceſſary duty? yea ſurely, it was Commanded by Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19. to be adminiſtred to all Diſciples; <hi>Diſciple all Nations, baptizing them,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>teaching them</hi> (that are ſo baptized) <hi>to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the ſame,</hi> verſ. 20. in the performance where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of Chriſt hath promiſed his continual Preſence: wherefore <hi>Peter</hi> gave this counſel to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed <hi>Jews,</hi> Act. 2.38. (that cried out in great terror, <hi>What ſhall we do?) Repent and be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized every one of you.</hi> As this was his advice to the diſtreſſed; ſo alſo it was to thoſe that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the holy Spirit plentifully. <hi>Acts</hi> 10.48. <hi>He commanded them to be baptized in the Name of the Lord.</hi> It ſeems it is an Ordinance meet to be obſerved by all ſorts of Chriſtians: the <hi>Jayler</hi> and his houſe, <hi>Acts</hi> 16.33. <hi>Lydia</hi> and her houſe, verſ. 15. <hi>Criſpus</hi> and his houſe, <hi>Acts</hi> 18.8. <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maria,</hi> Acts 8.12. the <hi>Eunuch,</hi> verſ. 38. yea, all (without exception) that gladly received the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:97824:28"/>
Word were baptized, and thereupon added to the Church, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.41.</p>
            <p>I might be large herein, but <hi>John Bunyan</hi> hath ſpared my labour, for he yields the caſe; and confeſſeth, <hi>pag.</hi> 122, 123. <hi>That Baptiſm is an holy Ordinance of God; a duty enjoyned ſuch who receive the Goſpel:</hi> And what can be more ſaid, if it be a duty enjoyned, it is a neceſſary duty; &amp;c. Wherefore I ſhall only add for Confirmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſome Arguments as follow, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 1. If the non-ſubjection to Baptiſm de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bars men from Church-Communion; Then the ſubjection thereto is neceſſary in order to Church-Communion: But the non-ſubjection to Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm debars men from Church-Communion: <hi>Ergo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Major</hi> is undeniable; the <hi>Minor</hi> I ſhall prove thus:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 2. If the walking diſorderly, not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Traditions received from the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, debars men from Church-Communion; Then the non-ſubjection to Baptiſm debars men from Church-Communion: But the walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſorderly, not according to the Traditions received from the Apoſtles, debars men from Church-Communion: <hi>Ergo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Minor</hi> is proved, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3.6. where the Apoſtle commands, <hi>That all who walk diſorderly not according to their Traditions, ſhould be debarred Communion.</hi> The <hi>Major</hi> I prove thus:</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:97824:29"/>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 3. If the non-ſubjection to Baptiſm be a diſorderly walking, not according to the Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Apoſtles; Then the <hi>Major</hi> is true: But the non-ſubjection to Baptiſm is a diſorder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly walking not according to the Traditions of the Apoſtles: <hi>Ergo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nothing in this Argument can be queſtioned, except the <hi>Minor,</hi> and that ſurely cannot be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied by <hi>John Bunyan,</hi> (with whom I have now to deal); for by his own Confeſſion, <hi>pag.</hi> 64. <hi>Baptiſm is an Ordinance of Jeſus Chriſt, an holy Ordinance of God,</hi> pag. 123. <hi>and that of excellent uſe to inſtruct in the moſt weighty matters of the Kingdom of God,</hi> p. 65. <hi>an enjoyned Duty,</hi> p. 122. <hi>an apparant Tradition of the Apoſtles; for in thoſe dayes</hi> (he confeſſeth, <hi>pag.</hi> 70.) <hi>it was adminiſtred upon Converſion, and uſed then to go before Church-Communion.</hi> Again,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 4. If the non-ſubjection to Baptiſm be a ſin againſt God, a rejecting the Counſel of God againſt our ſelves, and the breach of a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience; Then it debars men from Church-Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion: But the non-ſubjection to Baptiſm is a ſin againſt God, a rejecting the Counſel of God againſt our ſelves, and the breach of a good Conſcience: <hi>Ergo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Major</hi> I think none can deny; and the <hi>Minor</hi> is evident by <hi>John Bunyan</hi>'s own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, as aforeſaid, and the Scriptures before al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaged, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19. &amp; 7.29. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.21.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:97824:29"/>Further,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 5. If all Church-Members in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles dayes were baptized; Then Baptiſm is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to Church-Communion: But all Church-Members in the Apoſtles dayes were baptized: <hi>Ergo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One would think this Argument ſhould put the matter out of doubt; both Propoſitions be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing acknowledged by <hi>John Bunyan</hi> himſelf, yea, urged by him as weighty truths; for he makes the Example of the Primitive New-Teſtament-Churches the ground of his Communion, <hi>p.</hi> 52. yea, ſo far, that he ſaith, <hi>He dares not do other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than they did:</hi> And if we follow that Rule propoſed by himſelf, we muſt not do otherwiſe; and what then? Surely they baptized all Church-members before Communion, as he confeſſeth, <hi>pag.</hi> 91. But that I may not conclude with the Confeſſion of a man ſo various (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it may well be alleaged againſt himſelf) as in one little <hi>Treatiſe</hi> to ſpeak ſo many incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtencies; I ſhall proceed to another Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 6. If all Church-members are command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be baptized; Then the ſubjection to Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm is neceſſary to Church-Communion: But all Church-members are commanded to be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized: <hi>Ergo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Major</hi> is apparent; The <hi>Minor</hi> I prove thus:</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:97824:30"/>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 7. If Baptiſm is commanded to all Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples; Then it is commanded to all Church-members: But Baptiſm is commanded to all Diſciples: <hi>Ergo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No man can doubt of the truth of the <hi>Major,</hi> that believeth Church-members to be Diſciples, which I ſuppoſe no Chriſtian, in his right mind, will deny: And the <hi>Minor</hi> I ſhall prove from the words of Chriſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19, 20. <hi>Go teach all Nations, baptizing them, &amp;c.</hi> the Text is read, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: which being interpreted, is, <hi>Diſciple ye all Nations, baptizing them, &amp;c.</hi> (viz. thoſe that are Diſcipled, as by the Grammati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal conſtruction of the words may appear) <hi>teaching them</hi> (that is, the baptized Diſciples) <hi>to obſerve</hi> (or keep diligently) <hi>all things what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever I have commanded you:</hi> One whereof was, to baptize thoſe that were diſcipled. But it ſeems that either <hi>J. B.</hi> was never a baptized Diſciple, or that his Inſtructors forgot to teach him this Rule of Chriſt, or elſe he hath ſoon forgotten what he learned, if it be not a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe tranſgreſſing of what he knoweth, and ſo guilty of many ſtripes, <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.47.</p>
            <p>But to return; ſince <hi>John Bunyan</hi> is pleaſed (notwithſtanding his aforementioned Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) to deny Baptiſm to be the Rule of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion; let us hear what Rule he would have,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:97824:30"/>
which he thus declares, <hi>pag.</hi> 78. <hi>Even that rule by which they are diſcovered to the Church to be viſible Saints; and willing to be gathered into their Body and Fellowſhip.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Well ſaid; but how muſt that be if not by obedience to Chriſt's Ordinances, to the holy Ordinances of God, yea, the Principles of the Doctrine of Chriſt? is not the ſubjecting thereto a diſcovery of a viſible Saint, and a willingneſs to be gathered into the Body, even the Church?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>John Bunyan</hi> to this, <hi>pag.</hi> 79. anſwers, <hi>No: it is not</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the practiſing of a circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial,</hi> but <hi>the commendation of their Faith by the Word of Faith, and their converſation by a moral Precept;</hi> wherefore he tells us, <hi>pag.</hi> 79. <hi>That when</hi> Paul <hi>had declared his Faith, he falls down to the body of the Law, ſaying, Receive us, we have wronged no man, we have corrupted no man, we have defrauded no man,</hi> 2 Cor. 7.2. From whence (with divers ſuch Inſtances and Paraphraſes of his own thereupon) he concludes, <hi>pag.</hi> 79. <hi>That by the Word of Faith and good Works,</hi> (viz. <hi>Moral Duties Goſpelized) we ought to judge of the fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Members, by which we ought alſo to receive them into Fellowſhip.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> We read that <hi>Moſes</hi> put a vail over his face, to hinder the ſplendor of his countenance from dazling the eyes of the beholders; but, lo here, <hi>J. B.</hi> puts a vail over his face, to impede
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:97824:31"/>
the diſcovery of his perverting the Ordinances of God, and the Rule of Communion; which that I may ſo far put away, that he may appear as he is,</p>
            <p>Concerning what is ſaid; Conſider, Firſt, how this <hi>Theſis</hi> is conſiſtent with <hi>John Bunyan</hi>'s own judgment concerning Circumciſion: for ſure Baptiſm is not more a Circumſtance than that; yet, by his own grant, that was of old the Rule of Communion. Secondly, Why (in his ſenſe) he ſhould call Baptiſm a Circumſtance, I know not, it hath been proved a Principle of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Chriſt, a Foundation-principle, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.1. A neceſſary duty, a duty enjoyned to thoſe that receive the Goſpel; and is it notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all this but ſuch a Circumſtance; the Lord God of Heaven judge between us.</p>
            <p>Again; He comes to affirm; <hi>pag.</hi> 79. what is the Rule of Communion, <hi>viz. To have our Faith commended by the Word of Faith, and our Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation by a Moral Precept,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Wherein know, that the Word of Faith, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Paul</hi>'s mind, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.7, 8. is Chriſt: And what Faith doth he commend? ſurely not a bare Profeſſion which conſiſts only in words, but that Faith which preſently produceth obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience: For ſo he ſaith, <hi>Luk.</hi> 6.46. <hi>Why call ye me Lord, Lord, and do not the things that I ſay?</hi> (of which Baptiſm is one; yea, a great Duty): to which alſo the Apoſtle bares witneſs, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.3.
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:97824:31"/>
               <hi>He that ſaith he knoweth him, and keepeth not his Commandments</hi> (of which <hi>J. Bunyan</hi> confeſſeth Baptiſm to be one, and that of great uſe) <hi>is a lyar, and the truth is not in him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But perhaps <hi>John Bunyan</hi> will ſay, He would have works attend Faith, and therefore he adds, our Converſation muſt be commended by a Moral Precept.</p>
            <p>Wherein let me ask <hi>J. Bunyan,</hi> or any rational Chriſtian, how this is poſſible in divers caſes: as Firſt, upon Converſion, when men are preſently (upon the Preaching of the Word) turned from darkneſs to light, and ſo are received as Church-members, as ſoon as they are Converted, who before were Fornicators, Murtherers, Thieves, and what not, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.11. but upon their Converſion are received as Church-mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers even the ſame day, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.41. What ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience can there be of their Converſion who were Adulterers the day before? If you ſay they are changed now, let me tell you it muſt appear otherwiſe than by ſo ſhort forbearance (which is common with the worſt of men), or elſe they may be as bad as ever, and ſo <hi>John Bunyan</hi>'s Rule very uncertain.</p>
            <p>Secondly; The moſt Holy Converſation, in reference to what <hi>John Bunyan</hi> ſpeaks, cannot demonſtrate a Chriſtian (for there are Wolves in Sheeps clothing, <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.15.) neither is it ſufficient to be the Rule, the initiating Rule for
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:97824:32"/>
Church-Communion; it muſt be ſaid in this caſe as Chriſt once ſaid, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.20. <hi>Except your righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs exceed the righteouſneſs of the Scribes and Phariſees, ye cannot enter into the Kingdom of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</hi> Was not <hi>Paul</hi> exact in ſuch a Converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on before his Converſion? <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.6. and it cannot be imagined that he did degenerate af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards; and yet when <hi>Ananias</hi> was ſent to tell him what he muſt do, he delivers his Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage thus, <hi>Acts</hi> 22.16. <hi>Why tarrieſt thou? ariſe, and be baptized.</hi> Again, <hi>Cornelius</hi> was a devout and holy man, <hi>Acts</hi> 10.1. yet when he received the Truth and the Holy Spirit alſo abundantly, <hi>Peter</hi> commands him to be baptized, <hi>verſ.</hi> 46. Surely if <hi>John Bunyan</hi>'s Rule had been ſufficient, <hi>John the Baptiſt</hi> might then, upon good grounds, have forbad the Baptiſm of Chriſt; &amp; our Saviour, who fulfilled all thoſe Moral Precepts, needed not have ſaid, <hi>Thus it behooveth us</hi> (concerning Baptiſm) <hi>to fulfill all Righteouſneſs.</hi> Wherefore, although I muſt extol an holy Converſation in its due place, wherein I wiſh that (as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaith, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.19.) <hi>All that name the Name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, may depart from all ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity;</hi> yet let me tell you, The Apoſtle never urged any part of the moral Law, as the Rule of Communion under the Goſpel; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>John Bunyan</hi> is ſtrangely miſtaken, to adviſe us, to make uſe of the Ten Commandments, <hi>pag,</hi> 79. to judge of the fitneſs of perſons by; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:97824:32"/>
(if we have reſpect but to the 4th, which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyns the Sabbath ſo exactly, and upon ſuch a penalty) I cannot wonder that he ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit Chriſtian-tenderneſs would not be exceeded by ſuch ſtrictneſs, whenas Chriſtians are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted from judging one another therein, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.16. And truly I wonder more that a wiſe man ſhould alleage that inſtance of <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 Cor. 7.2. as a Rule for Church-Communion, when as he knows it was ſpoken to ſuch as were begotten to the Faith through <hi>Paul</hi>'s Miniſtry; and it is then ſtrange, that he ſhould offer that as a Rule for his reception amongſt them, when that in truth he ſpeaks not at all in reference to Church-Communion, but in a holy boaſting of his own behaviour, and the reſt of the Apoſtles, for the ornament of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>Which notwithſtanding <hi>John Bunyan,</hi> pag. 80. fraudulently proceeds to defame the holy Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Baptiſm, urging that it is ſaid, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.18. <hi>The Kingdom of God, or our ſervice to Chriſt</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>conſiſts not in meats and drinks, but in righteouſneſs, peace, and joy in the holy Ghoſt; and he that in theſe things ſerveth Chriſt, is accepted of God, and approved of men:</hi> which he after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards tells you, <hi>pag.</hi> 81. is meant <hi>of the Law gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven upon Sinai,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw. John Bunyan</hi> ſaith, <hi>pag.</hi> 45. That <hi>he believes that Jeſus Chriſt by the Word of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, will judge all men at the day of Doom:</hi>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:97824:33"/>
But ſure, if in his heart he thought ſo, he would be afraid of a ſharp cenſure, if not the addition of many plagues, for adding to the words of God, and ſetting his poſt by the Lord's, which here he doth in telling you, That <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Our ſervice to Chriſt conſiſts not in meats or drinks,</hi> &amp;c. when that it is the Kingdom of God he ſpeaks of; which in this place I never read was under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of our ſervice to Chriſt: But if ſo, what doth this reſpect Baptiſm? The Apoſtle ſpeaks only of meats and drinks, which you may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive by his words, the <hi>Romans</hi> (which <hi>J. B.</hi> confeſſeth were baptized) did differ about; which things alſo <hi>Paul</hi> (where he exalts Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm) doth ſpeak againſt: wherefore what all this is to the matter in hand, let a wiſe man judge, except to ſhew <hi>John Bunyan</hi>'s ſingulari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; which alſo appears in his Explication of Righteouſneſs, Peace, and Joy in the holy Ghoſt, which (with many fair gloſſes) he would have you to believe to be the moral Law given upon <hi>Sinai,</hi> which (notwithſtanding what he ſaith) appears not only an addition, but even ſuch a one as is inconſiſtent with the Scripture. For, Firſt, <hi>Righteouſneſs, (Paul</hi> tells you) <hi>comes not by the Law,</hi> viz. the Law given upon <hi>Sinai, Gal.</hi> 2.21. Secondly, Peace cannot come by it, becauſe it cannot give life, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.21. neither joy; for it could never make the comers thereunto perfect; and what joy or peace in ſuch an
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:97824:33"/>
Eſtate there can be, or in ſuch a Law, I know not.</p>
            <p>But in truth, the <hi>righteouſneſs, peace, and joy in the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> which the Apoſtle ſpeaks of, is none other but that which Chriſtians are made partakers of in Chriſt Jeſus, without the works of the Law, (and therefore to ſay we muſt do this Righteouſneſs, is to derogate the honour of Chriſt) and he that in the fruition thereof ſerveth Chriſt according to his appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments (of which Baptiſm is confeſſed to be one of great uſe) is accepted of God, and approv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of men, without looking back to <hi>Sinai,</hi> which <hi>J. Bunyan</hi> falſly calls, <hi>pag.</hi> 81. <hi>a perfect Law,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Scriptures, and the holy men of old, who call it <hi>weak</hi> and <hi>unprofitable,</hi> Heb. 7.18. that which could not give life, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.21. or righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.21. nor make any of the comers thereunto perfect, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.19.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But ſtay,</hi> ſaith <hi>John Bunyan,</hi> pag. 81. <hi>although this of old was declared thereof, now the moral Precept Evangelized is perfect.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But may not I herein uſe <hi>John Bunyan</hi>'s own words, and turn them againſt himſelf, as one juſtly guilty of Fictions, and Scriptureleſs Notions: for, where do you read in Scripture of the Law Evangelized? Surely the contrary is often found; and although <hi>James</hi> (as it is urged by <hi>John Bunyan</hi>) Chap. 2. prelling love, which he calls the Royal Law, (and indeed was
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:97824:34"/>
before the Law given upon <hi>Sinai,</hi> 1 Joh. 2.7.) urgeth it to be according to what was before written, yet he doth not call the Law given up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Sinai,</hi> the <hi>Royal Law,</hi> or the <hi>Law of Liberty,</hi> as <hi>J. Bunyan</hi> falſly pretends, contrary to <hi>Paul</hi>'s words, who ſaith, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.24. <hi>It was a Law</hi> (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though as much Evangelized in his dayes as now) <hi>which gendreth to bondage,</hi> yea, the Ten Commandments (written in ſtone) (ſo exalt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>John Bunyan</hi>), he calls <hi>the miniſtration of death,</hi> 2 Cor. 3.7. <hi>of condemnation,</hi> verſ. 9. and placeth it in oppoſition to the miniſtration of the Spirit, and of Righteouſneſs, which is the glorious Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt, that needeth not have any recourſe to the Law, being in it ſelf much more perfect, as indeed the Law of Liberty which <hi>James</hi> intends; As alſo <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.2. <hi>The Law of the Spirit of Life in Chriſt Jeſus, hath made me free from the Law of ſin and death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore in ſhort, The Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> doth not (as <hi>John Bunyan</hi> pretends) exalt the Law given upon <hi>Sinai,</hi> as the Rule of Communion, but writing to the Brethren of the diſperſed Twelve Tribes, whom he well knew were zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of the Law, he endeavours thereby to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince them of their Duty, as Chriſt did to the <hi>Jews,</hi> Joh. 5.39, 45. And <hi>Paul</hi> the Heathens, by the words of their own Poets, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.28. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming the Truth by the witneſs of themſelves,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:97824:34"/>
               <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.12. as I alſo often take occaſion to do, from <hi>J. Bunyan</hi> his own Confeſſion, although I ſhould be as far from making his words the Rule of Truth, as <hi>Paul</hi> the writings of the Heathen Poets, which never were alleaged to that end; yet. <hi>J. Bunyan</hi> might as well affirm it, as to ſay that <hi>James,</hi> Chap. 2. calls the Law given upon <hi>Sinai, the Law of Liberty,</hi> which alſo he is pleaſed to avouch as the Rule of Communion, <hi>pag.</hi> 82. alleaging the words of <hi>Paul, I am un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law to Chriſt;</hi> which ſure (as he ſhun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned naming the place) he might have been a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed to have inſtanced in this caſe, it being only a Parentheſis in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.21. where <hi>Paul</hi> having declared his endeavours to gain many, that it might not be thought (<hi>John Bunyan</hi>-like) he would wave Chriſt's Ordinances, or pervert his Doctrine; he tells us, That in all this his condeſcention (before ſpoken of) he is not without Law to God, but under the Law to Chriſt, having (as if he ſhould have ſaid) great reſpect to his holy Ordinances, (which muſt not be violated by any means); not the Law of <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nai,</hi> for (if himſelf may be heard) he ſaith, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.19. That <hi>he was dead to that, and that dead to him,</hi> as is confirmed, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.1, 2, 3. by the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of a Widow whoſe Husband is dead; from whence the Apoſtle concludes, <hi>verſ.</hi> 6. That we are delivered from the Law, that being dead wherein we were held; whereupon ſure it may
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:97824:35"/>
be concluded of <hi>John Bunyan,</hi> as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, 1 Tim. 1.7. <hi>He would be a Teacher of the Law, although he underſtandeth neither what he ſaith, nor whereof he affirms;</hi> (although we know the Law is good, if a man uſe it lawfully) as far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther appeareth in that Diſtich, <hi>pag.</hi> 83. where he ſaith, <hi>Communion is forbidden with ſuch as live in the tranſgreſſion of a moral Precept,</hi> alleaging <hi>Paul</hi>'s words, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.11. <hi>If any man that is called a Brother, be a Fornicator, or Covetous, or an Idolator, or a Railer, or a Drunkard, or an Extortioner, with ſuch a one no not to eat:</hi> Paul <hi>ſaith not (John Bunyan</hi> tells you) <hi>if any man be not baptized, or joyn with the unbaptized, theſe</hi> (ſaith <hi>J. B.) are fictions and Scriptureleſs-notions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I muſt ſay to <hi>John Bunyan</hi> herein, as was ſaid to <hi>Peter,</hi> Matth. 26.73. <hi>Thy ſpeech be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrayeth thee: If any man that is called a Brother, &amp;c.</hi> They were Church-members whom theſe words were ſpoken of, and already baptized (by <hi>John Bunyan</hi>'s own grant) and therefore <hi>Paul</hi> needed not to ſay, <hi>If any be unbaptized,</hi> for there was none ſuch amongſt them: but it ſeems there were ſome that ſo far degenerated from their Profeſſion, as to be guilty of ſome of the aforeſaid Evils; wherefore <hi>Paul</hi> tells them, (without the Law of <hi>Sinai</hi>) they ought to be excluded from the Church, for the Goſpel of Chriſt Jeſus permits none ſuch wicked perſons to be retained. We ſay therefore, Although upon
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:97824:35"/>
Confeſſion of Faith, and ſubmiſſion to Baptiſm, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> We ought to receive perſons into Fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and Church-Communion, according to the pattern of the Primitive Churches; yet if any ſuch ſhall be guilty of the aforeſaid Evils, they muſt be again ſeparated according to the bleſſed Rule of Chriſt, which <hi>Paul</hi> by the afore-ſaid words intends; wherein, although he doth not ſay, If any man be unbaptized, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (having then no occaſion for ſuch words) yet ſure it is great impudence in <hi>John Bunyan</hi> to ſay they are Fictions, and Scriptureleſs Notions. Is it a Fiction to deny Communion with thoſe that are diſobedient to a Principle of Chriſt's Doctrine? is that a ſcriptureleſs Notion? Doth not the Scripture ſay, <hi>If any man tranſgreſſeth and abideth not in the Doctrine of Chriſt</hi> (whereof Baptiſm is a part) <hi>he hath not God?</hi> 2 Joh. 9. and <hi>v.</hi> 10. <hi>If any man come</hi> (like <hi>John Bunyan) and bring not that Doctrine,</hi> he <hi>is to be rejected.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to colour the deſign, <hi>John Bunyan</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds to tell the World, <hi>pag.</hi> 83. <hi>That the Word of Faith, and the Moral Precept, is that which</hi> Paul <hi>enjoyns the</hi> Galatians <hi>and</hi> Philippians, <hi>ſtill avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing outward Circumſtances</hi> (he might as well have ſaid Baptiſm): <hi>Hence therefore</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>when he had treated of Faith, he falls point-blank upon moral Duties, urging,</hi> pag. 84. <hi>that in Chriſt neither Circumciſion nor <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncircumciſion availeth any thing, but a new Creature;</hi> and <hi>that peace is
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:97824:36"/>
promiſed to as many as walk according to this Rule, Gal.</hi> 6.15, 16. Which Rule (he would have you believe) excludes Baptiſm; and therefore he adds, <hi>pag.</hi> 86. <hi>In Chriſt Jeſus no outward or Circumſtantial thing, but a new Creature,</hi> (wherein he proceeds to tell us a fair tale): from whence he concludes, <hi>pag.</hi> 90. <hi>That ſeeing Baptiſm is no initiating Ordinance, nor viſible Character of a Saint, no breach in a good and holy life, nor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trencheth upon any man's right but his own; Faith may be effectual without it, and his life approved by the worſt of his enemies, he may keep the Law: wherefore his friends ſhould not diſhonour God in breaking the Law;</hi> Alleaging the words of <hi>James, Chap.</hi> 4.11. <hi>Speak not evil of one another, Brethren; for he that ſpeaketh evil of his Brother, ſpeaketh evil of the Law, and judgeth the Law:</hi> From whence he reaſons, <hi>That the failer muſt be in a Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, for which he ought not to be judged.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> To all this I muſt anſwer in the words of <hi>Paul,</hi> Acts 13.10. <hi>Oh! full of all ſubtilty and miſchief, wilt thou not ceaſe to pervert the right wayes of the Lord?</hi> Were not the <hi>Galati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> and <hi>Philippians,</hi> to whom the Apoſtle wrote, Church-members, and baptized by thy own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion? Did the Apoſtle, in any of his Epiſtles, avoid Baptiſm in reference to Church-Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, or count it ſuch a Circumſtance as thou doſt? Did not <hi>Paul</hi> exalt it even to the <hi>Gala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians, Chap.</hi> 3.27. where he demonſtrates their
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:97824:36"/>
Faith thereby? For, ſaith he, as <hi>many as have been boptized into Chriſt, have put on Chriſt.</hi> Can the Evangelical Precepts be enjoyned without it? Was it ever ſaid, that in Chriſt Jeſus Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, or no Baptiſm, availeth not? Was it ever ſaid (in Scripture) in Chriſt Jeſus, no outward or circumſtantial thing, but a new Creature? Is not this contrary to the Rule of the Apoſtles? Why art thou ſo bold to pervert the right ways of the Lord, as to conclude Baptiſm (which hath been proved a Principle, a firſt Principle of the Doctrine of Chriſt, a neceſſary Duty) to be no initiating Ordinance; no, nor the viſible Character of a Saint, no breach in a good and holy life? What, is not obedience to Chriſt, to an holy Ordinance, to a Duty enjoyned, a cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of a Saint, yea a viſible character? is not the contrary a breach, ſome breach at leaſt in a good and holy life? Surely, if thy ſenſes were not ſtupified, thou wouldſt never deny it, nor once mention (for juſtification thereof) that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience to Baptiſm intrencheth upon no man's right but his own. What is Infidelity, is it not a horrid ſin?</p>
            <p>But ſaith <hi>John Bunyan, Whoſe right doth it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trench upon but their own?</hi> The God of Heaven ſaith, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 3.9. <hi>Wo unto their Soul, they have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded evil to themſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>J.B.</hi> ſayes, <hi>His Faith may be effectual with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it, and his Life approved by the worſt of his Enemies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:97824:37"/>Touching his Faith let the God of Heaven anſwer, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.3. <hi>He that ſayeth he knoweth me, and keepeth not my Commandments, is a lyar:</hi> And concerning his Life, I muſt ſay with the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.18. <hi>Not he that commendeth himſelf is approved, but whom the Lord commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth:</hi> Wherefore if he may keep the Law (as thou ſayeſt) know it is not the Law of Chriſt, for that requires Baptiſm, and therefore no circumſtantial, as the failer therein muſt not be judged; and therefore in this place the Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on offered by thy ſelf, <hi>pag.</hi> 91. is well placed, <hi>viz. But notwithſtanding all that hath been ſaid, Water-Baptiſm ought to go before Church-memberſhip; ſhew me one in all the New-Teſtament that was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived into Fellowſhip without it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Sure, <hi>J. Bunyan,</hi> when thou didſt Pen this Objection, thy craft deceived thee, and thou didſt not ſee how thou haſt enſnared thy ſelf; What anſwer canſt thou make?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>John Bunyan</hi> will ſay, he hath a ready anſwer, which conſiſts in two parts. <hi>Firſt</hi> (ſaith he, <hi>pag.</hi> 91.) <hi>that Water-Baptiſm hath formerly gone firſt, is granted: but that it ought of neceſſity ſo to do, I never ſaw proof.</hi> Secondly (he ſaith) <hi>None ever received it without Light, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> Firſt <hi>John Bunyan</hi> here confeſſeth, <hi>That Water-Baptiſm went before Church-memberſhip in the Primitive Times:</hi> Well ſaid, <hi>John Bunyan,</hi> thou haſt given away the Cauſe, and overthrown
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:97824:37"/>
thy ſelf. If it did ſo then, ſure it muſt now, for we are to walk according to their Examples, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.17. It ſeems God is ſtronger and wiſer too than the Devil, he hath made a hedge about Water-baptiſm that it ſhould not be violated, but inſtead thereof acknowledged for truth (e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven) by its Enemies.</p>
            <p>But <hi>John Bunyan</hi> ſaith, <hi>He never ſaw it proved to be of neceſſity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> What, <hi>John Bunyan,</hi> how now! did the Apoſtles practiſe generally what they ought not? ſure in plain terms thou wilt not ſay ſo; and if not ſo, it was their duty, and there was neceſſity for them to do their duty.</p>
            <p>But then, ſecondly, <hi>John Bunyan</hi> ſaith, <hi>None ever received it without Light going before.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> See if this man be not ſtupified in his ſenſes whilſt he contends againſt the Truth; for he hath loſt the matter in queſtion: Who ever pretended that any received Baptiſm (upon good grounds) without light in it?</p>
            <p>The queſtion is not, who have Light therein, but who ought to have Light therein? <hi>viz. Whether it is the duty of Chriſtians, before Church-memberſhip, to be baptized?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein (for Anſwer) I will offer <hi>John Bunyan</hi>'s own words; <hi>Baptiſm</hi> (ſaith he, <hi>pag.</hi> 122.) <hi>is a Duty enjoyned to thoſe who receive the Goſpel.</hi> Again, <hi>pag.</hi> 82. <hi>In the Primitive times it was generally practiſed firſt (viz.</hi> before
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:97824:38"/>
Church-Communion) <hi>yea ſo as the unconverted themſelves, knew it belonged to the Diſciples of Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> What can we have more than is here acknowledged? Surely, if it was ſo ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally practiſed before Communion in the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Churches; it ought to be ſo now. Did the unconverted then know it was the duty of Chriſt's Diſciples to be baptized, as aforeſaid? and muſt it be queſtioned now by <hi>John Bunyan,</hi> or any pretending themſelves Chriſtians? Was it then a duty enjoyned to thoſe that receive the Goſpel? and is it not ſo now? ſurely yea. It may from hence be hoped, that <hi>John Bunyan</hi> is become a new man, and repents what he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends in the beginning of his Book.</p>
            <p>But ſtay, he is preſently of another mind, for he again ſaith, <hi>pag.</hi> 82. <hi>That all that were received into Fellowſhip, were even then baptized firſt, would ſtrain a weak man's wit to prove, if Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments were cloſly made from theſe three Texts of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scripture,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.14. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.27. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.3.</p>
            <p>What, <hi>John Bunyan,</hi> art thou ſo unſtable? I now underſtand plainly that Text of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.8. <hi>A double-minded man is unſtable in all his wayes;</hi> for he that wavereth is like a Wave of the Sea, driven with the wind and toſſed: even ſo is this man, who in the ſame <hi>page</hi> of a little <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> confeſſeth Baptiſm to be a general Practice in the Primitive times before Communion, and yet again ſaith, it would ſtrain
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:97824:38"/>
a weak man's wit to prove it. But ſurely <hi>John Bunyan</hi> means a Fool that knoweth not to prove any thing; (and ſuch a one as he, cannot in <hi>John Bunyan</hi>'s apprehenſion maintain, will never hurt the practice of Baptiſm) otherwiſe it may be proved from his own Confeſſion, if that be worth any thing. But it ſeems that may be contradicted, if Arguments were cloſly made upon the aforementioned Texts, wherein I ſhall adviſe <hi>John Bunyan</hi> (ſince he thinks ſo) the next time he meddleth in the derogation of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, to make his Arguments from them.</p>
            <p>But, Sir, if you do, pray, (according to your own words) do them more cloſly than you have already, otherwiſe your fallacy will be diſcovered, and your Arguments fall to the ground.</p>
            <p>But I perceive he is willing (as he ſaith, <hi>pag.</hi> 82.) <hi>To paſs thoſe Texts at preſent,</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of making Arguments thence-from, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends that if we can <hi>ſhew the Chriſtian that in the Primitive times remained dark about it, then he will ſhew the Chriſtian that was received into Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip without it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well ſaid, Mr. <hi>Bunyan;</hi> When the sky falls, you will catch Larks. You have already told us the Primitive Chriſtians all believed it, yea the <hi>unconverted knew</hi> (as you ſay) <hi>it did belong to the Diſciples of Chriſt,</hi> and yet you would now know the Chriſtian that was dark therein; and in that you know that to be impoſſible (if your
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:97824:39"/>
own words be true) therefore you offer if we do that, then you will ſhew the Chriſtian that was received without Baptiſm; which you well know is alſo impoſſible to be done: Wherefore to ſhew your reſoluteneſs, right or wrong, we have this <hi>Theſis</hi> from you, <hi>pag.</hi> 82. <hi>That if you ſhould grant</hi> (which you ſay is more than can be proved; but it is but your ſay ſo) <hi>Baptiſm to be an initiating Ordinance, and that it did, as Circumciſion of old, give a being of memberſhip to the partakers; yea, ſet the caſe men were forbidden to enter into Fellowſhip without it; yet the caſe may ſo be that (theſe things notwithſtanding), men might be received into Fellowſhip without it.</hi> Where are we now? what is <hi>John Bunyan</hi> not content to ſet his poſts by the Lord's poſts; but Antichriſt-like, he muſt needs advance him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf above God? 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.4. giving new Laws contrary to what the God of Heaven hath given in his Son Jeſus Chriſt. If Baptiſm be an initia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Ordinance, and gives a being to Member<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; yet all that avails nothing with <hi>J. Bunyan,</hi> he will receive members without it, and that in deſpite of God, although he hath forbidden it. What Doctrine is this? Would you know a reaſon of his Practice which he pretends to ſhew you? In ſhort, it is his will, maugre all oppoſition, even of God himſelf. For ſet the caſe men are forbidden by the Lord to enter into
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:97824:39"/>
Fellowſhip without Baptiſm, yet <hi>J. Bunyan</hi> will receive them.</p>
            <p>But let us hear what he pretends as his war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, <hi>pag.</hi> 83. And that is firſt, <hi>the Example of the</hi> Jews <hi>in the Wilderneſs, who</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding Circumciſion, gave a being to Church-memberſhip, without which it was</hi> (if you will believe <hi>John Bunyan) poſitively commanded none ſhould be received into Fellowſhip, yet for all this more than ſix hundred thouſand were received in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Church without it, and alſo retained there, and that even by</hi> Moſes <hi>and</hi> Joſhua.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> To this Poſition I ſhall ſay, Firſt, Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion never gave a being to Church-mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berſhip, neither was there any ſuch poſitive Command (as is pretended) that none ſhould be received into the Church without it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>John Bunyan</hi> I ſuppoſe will grant the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, for ſure he will allow Holy Women to be Church-members.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The ſix hundred thouſand were not received into Fellowſhip by <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhua,</hi> neither were they any wayes accompted by them Church-members; but as they were the natural ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> to whom the Promiſe was made.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Their neglect of Circumciſion was an evil, and a reproach to them, which was ſaid to be <hi>rolled away</hi> in their Circumciſion, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 5.9. wherefore, whatſoever was the impediment, it
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:97824:40"/>
matters not; it was a ſin in them, and a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach unto them, although <hi>J. Bunyan</hi> pretends they had a legal reaſon to excuſe it, <hi>which alſo</hi> (as he thinks, or at leaſt ſaith, <hi>pag.</hi> 94.) <hi>many have in theſe dayes to neglect Baptiſm, although an enjoyned Duty, an holy Ordinance of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What excuſe (I mean legal) can that be?</p>
            <p>He ſaith, <hi>The want of Light: Our Brethren</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>have a manifeſt reaſon, an invincible one, one that all the men on Earth, or Angels in Heaven cannot remove; for it is God that createth Light: wherefore, if</hi> Moſes <hi>and</hi> Joſhua <hi>thought fit to Communicate with the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncircumciſed as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, why may not I have Communion, yea, the cloſeſt Communion with viſible Saints, although they want Light in, and cannot ſubmit to that?</hi> (meaning Baptiſm) <hi>I ſhall therefore</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>hold Communion with ſuch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Who could ever have thought that <hi>John Bunyan</hi> ſhould have Preached the Doctrine of thoſe perſons, againſt whom he hath ſo fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently manifeſted inveterate hatred? He hath often cryed out againſt others for ſaying, <hi>The Light within is the Rule for Chriſtians to walk by;</hi> but now he himſelf confidently affirms it, yea, in oppoſition to poſitive Commands, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Prohibitions, making it the great reaſon for and againſt a Practice; yea, ſuch a one <hi>as neither Men or Angels can remove.</hi> But this is
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:97824:40"/>
no ſtrange thing: <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Pilate,</hi> two great Enemies, agreed in one againſt Chriſt.</p>
            <p>But let me ask <hi>J. Bunyan,</hi> Whether Light makes a thing to be a Duty or no Duty? is God's Law ſubſervient to our Light?</p>
            <p>I ſuppoſe he muſt anſwer, <hi>Yea;</hi> for it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruous with his reaſoning, that what God Commands, is no Duty to thoſe that have no Light therein; or, at leaſt, the want of Light is a ſufficient excuſe for the neglect thereof; <hi>For</hi> (ſaith he, <hi>pag.</hi> 94.) <hi>God creates Light</hi> (I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe he means); <hi>therefore if they have no Light, it is becauſe God hath not given it, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well would it be, if this be ſo, for the greateſt part of men to have ſuch an Advocate as <hi>John Bunyan</hi> at the laſt day, to plead on the behalf of their diſobedience, that they wanted Light to do otherwiſe; yea, that God never gave them Light. If the Rich man we read of, <hi>Luke</hi> 16. had but in this condition, had <hi>John Bunyan</hi> to plead for him, his mouth would not have been ſo ſoon ſtopped.</p>
            <p>But ſtay, I remember Chriſt ſaid unto the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable Servant, <hi>Luk.</hi> 19.22. <hi>Out of thine own mouth will I judge thee:</hi> And what if it ſhould be ſo ſaid to <hi>John Bunyan,</hi> where would he be then? and what would become of his Brethren under whoſe arm-holes he hath ſowed pillows? Doth not he ſay, <hi>pag.</hi> 45. <hi>I believe Jeſus Chriſt by the Word of the Scriptures, will judge all men
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:97824:41"/>
at the day of Doom?</hi> And if ſo, the Word of the Scriptures ſaith, <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.48. <hi>He that knew not his Lord's Will (viz.</hi> hath no Light in it) <hi>ſhall be beaten; and</hi> good reaſon, for the want of Light is through their own neglect; <hi>the Light ſhined in darkneſs, but the darkneſs comprehended it not,</hi> Joh. 1.5. It hath been before proved, That <hi>this is the Condemnation, that Light is come into the World; but men love darkneſs rather than Light,</hi> Joh. 3.19. Would <hi>J. Bunyan</hi> think it a ſufficient reaſon againſt Faith, for a man to ſay, I have no Light? If it be a good reaſon in one thing, it is good in all. <hi>Paul</hi> once ſaid, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.9. <hi>I was alive without the Law,</hi> at leaſt he thought ſo when he did not know Sin; which by <hi>John Bunyan</hi>'s reaſon is a ſufficient excuſe for any evil, if I want Light to do otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>But ſurely <hi>John Bunyan</hi> is conſcious to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, that notwithſtanding what he hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended concerning the weight of the aforeſaid Reaſon, which he ſaith is invincible; yea, ſo that all the men on Earth, or Angels in Heaven can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not remove; I ſay, he is conſcious of the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and fallacy thereof; otherwiſe he would never have ſpent ſo much time in vain, as to alleage afterwards <hi>Ten</hi> other <hi>Reaſons</hi> to confirm his Opinion and Practice, when he had done it ſo invincibly before; unleſs therewith (as the Red Dragon with his ten horns) he is minded ſo to puſh againſt the Truth, that he might
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:97824:41"/>
overthrow it root and branch. For the preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion whereof (although it need not much be feared from <hi>John Bunyan</hi>) I ſhall adventure a further encounter to try the ſtrength of his Weapons, and the force of his Reaſons: The firſt is this:</p>
            <p>Reaſ. 1. <hi>Becauſe the true viſible Saint hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſubjected to that which is better, even to the Righteouſneſs of God, which is by Faith in Jeſus Chriſt, &amp;c. He is therefore to be received, not by thy light, not for that in Circumſtances he jumpeth with thy Opinion, but according to his own Faith, which he ought to keep to himſelf before God, as</hi> Paul <hi>ſaith,</hi> 1 Cor. 10.29. <hi>Conſcience I ſay, not of thy own, but of the other, &amp;c.</hi> pag. 94, 95.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Here you have <hi>John Bunyan</hi>'s firſt <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> wherein he tells you, the true viſible Saint hath ſubjected to that which is better. But can a man be a true viſible Saint, that viſibly oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth Chriſt's Ordinances? <hi>He that hath my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, and keepeth them,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.21. <hi>he it is that loveth me; he is my friend,</hi> Joh. 15.14. And our Saviour renders the Reaſon thereof, <hi>Chap.</hi> 14.23. <hi>If any man love me, he will keep my words:</hi> And again, <hi>verſ.</hi> 24. <hi>He that keepeth not my ſayings, loveth me not,</hi> (ſurely without offence I may add) <hi>Is no true viſible Saint.</hi> But <hi>John Bunyan</hi> (not forgetting to oppoſe the Lord Chriſt) will vindicate ſuch diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:97824:42"/>
and tell you <hi>the Saint he deſcribeth hath ſubjected to that which is better.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well, be it ſo; doth it therefore follow the leſs muſt be deſpiſed? I hope <hi>John Bunyan</hi> will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, <hi>The life is more than meat, and the Body than raiment;</hi> yet the leſſer muſt be received for the preſervation of the greater. Beſides, had not <hi>Paul</hi> the greater when he was Converted to the Faith? Yet <hi>Ananias</hi> (although he was inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that he was a choſen Veſſel, which was the better) commands him to be baptized, <hi>Acts</hi> 22.16. Had not <hi>Cornelius</hi> and his Companions the greater, when their hearts were purified by Faith, and alſo repleniſhed with the Holy Spirit, <hi>Acts</hi> 10.44. <hi>Chap.</hi> 11.15, 17. yet <hi>Peter</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands them to be baptized. Yea, had not Chriſt himſelf the greater, to whom the Spirit was not given by meaſure, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.34. Yet when <hi>John</hi> (peradventure upon the ſame account as <hi>John Bunyan</hi> pretends) forbad his Baptiſm, <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.14. Chriſt anſwers, <hi>verſ.</hi> 15. <hi>Suffer it to be ſo, for thus it behooveth us to fulfil all righteouſneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Baptiſm, it ſeems, is no indifferent thing, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though <hi>John Bunyan</hi> would have you believe it ſo, alleaging as aforeſaid the words of <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.29. which words only have reſpect to the eating of meats, which were permitted, (although not enjoyned) wherein (therefore) if a weak Brother ſhould be offended, they were adviſed not to eat for Conſcience ſake; <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:97824:42"/>
ſaith <hi>Paul, not of thy own</hi> (for it is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in it ſelf) <hi>but of the other</hi> (who thinks it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful): touching which <hi>J. Bunyan</hi> pretends (that you might think him to make his way plain) it may be objected, that what the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles wrote, they wrote to ſuch as were bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, and therefore the Arguments in the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtles, about things Circumſtantial, reſpect not the caſe in hand.</p>
            <p>To which he anſwers, <hi>Firſt, that this is a miſtake, the firſt to the</hi> Corinthians, <hi>the Epiſtle of</hi> James, <hi>the firſt and ſecond of</hi> Peter, <hi>the firſt E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle of</hi> John, <hi>were expreſly written to all the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as well as to particular Churches.</hi> pag. 86.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>That if Water-baptiſm (as the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances with which the Churches were peſtered of old) trouble their peace, wound the Conſciences of the Godly, diſmember, and break their Fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; it is, although an Ordinance for the preſent, to be prudently ſhunned; for the Edification of the Churches is to be preferred before it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Touching this, as is here ſaid, I muſt tell you firſt <hi>J. Bunyan</hi> is miſtaken; and ſure he either miſtakes or forgets himſelf; for is not this the ſame <hi>J. Bunyan</hi> who in the ſame <hi>Treatiſe</hi> confeſſed, <hi>pag.</hi> 91. <hi>That in the Apoſtles dayes Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm went before Church-Communion:</hi> Yea, he further ſaith, <hi>pag.</hi> 92. <hi>It was then generally pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed by all Diſciples,</hi> and if ſo, then ſure the
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:97824:43"/>
fore-mentioned Epiſtles (although general) were directed to baptized perſons.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Thoſe things which the Apoſtles treat of as indifferent, were ſuch only, as were permitted either to be done, or not done; wherein many times there was no expedience in the performance thereof; as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith in the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forementioned, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.23. <hi>All things are law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, but all things are not expedient.</hi> Wherein he alſo ſaith, <hi>All things edify not;</hi> and therefore adviſeth, <hi>That no man ſhould ſeek his own, but every man his Brothers wealth:</hi> but there is no ſuch indifferency in Baptiſm, which hath been proved a neceſſary Duty; if that be a Circumſtance, it is a neceſſary Circumſtance that muſt be performed; Although <hi>J. Bunyan</hi> ſuppoſeth it may peſter the Churches, trouble their Peace, wound their Conſciences, &amp;c. wherefore in his judgment, although an Ordinance, to be ſhunned.</p>
            <p>How! Do Chriſt's holy Ordinances ever pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter the Churches, trouble their Peace, wound the Conſciences of the Godly, diſmember and break their Fellowſhip: I never heard it ſo to do; (but very efficacious on the contrary); But if ſo, let me tell you, it is an evil ſign (even as when the ſtomach is offended with wholeſome food) A ſign of an evil heart, from whence undoubtedly the cauſe thereof proceeds; But I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> think, it is but the deluſion of <hi>John
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:97824:43"/>
Bunyan</hi> to conceit it, as once <hi>Ahab</hi> counted the holy Prophet <hi>Elijah,</hi> the troubler of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 18.17.</p>
            <p>Wherefore herein let us not be perſwaded to ſhun that which ought to be imbraced; But ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as <hi>David</hi> ſaid to <hi>Michael,</hi> 2 Sam. 6.22. let us reſolve, that if it be accounted vile and evil to obey our God in his Holy Ordinances; <hi>We will yet be more vile:</hi> Thus much for the anſwer to his firſt Reaſon. His ſecond follows.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 2. Obſerve ſecondly, <hi>One Spirit, one Hope, one Lord, one Faith, one Baptiſm, not of Water, for by one Spirit are we all baptized into one body, one God and Father of all, and through all, and in you all, is a ſufficient Rule for us to hold Communion by, &amp; alſo to endeavour the maintaining that Communion, and to keep it in unity, within the bond of peace, againſt all attempts whatſoever,</hi> p. 96.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> What preſumption is this, in wreſting the Holy Scripture which perſwadeth to unity, (amongſt other Reaſons) becauſe there is one Baptiſm!</p>
            <p>But <hi>John Bunyan would have fellowſhip with the unbaptized</hi> (contrary to what is here inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the Apoſtle) <hi>and that</hi> (as he ſaith) <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this one Baptiſm is not of Water.</hi> Although the Text ſaith no ſuch thing, and <hi>John Bunyan</hi> himſelf hath often acknowledged, <hi>Baptiſm of Water to be an Holy Ordinance of Chriſt,</hi> pag. 123. <hi>generally practiſed,</hi> pag. 92. And then, if one
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:97824:44"/>
Baptiſm, what other, but that one (<hi>viz.</hi> Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm of Water) ſo generally practiſed by all Diſciples?</p>
            <p>He will tell us the Baptiſm of the Spirit, for <hi>by one Spirit are we all baptized into one body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which I anſwer, The Baptiſm of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit was not general, and ſo could not be intended by one Baptiſm.</p>
            <p>Secondly, It is not meant in the aforeſaid Text, which ſaith <hi>by,</hi> not <hi>with, one Spirit:</hi> for, in truth, thoſe that are baptized with Water, are by one Spirit, in one Faith, having one Hope, in one Lord, even one God and Father of all, baptized with one (<hi>viz.</hi> Water) Baptiſm, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to one Body and Fellowſhip, which ought therefore to be kept free from <hi>John Bunyan</hi>'s mixture.</p>
            <p>His Third Reaſon follows, <hi>pag.</hi> 97. viz. <hi>I am bold therefore to have Communion with ſuch, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they alſo have the Doctrine of Baptiſms, I ſay the Doctrine of them: For here you muſt note, I diſtinguiſh between the Doctrine and Practice of Water-baptiſm, &amp;c. they have the beſt of Baptiſms; the heart of Water-baptiſm, the Doctrine of Water-baptiſm, and want only the Sign, the outward Circumſtance, which is forborn for want of Light.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Oh Lord, what deluſions are here! Righteous art thou in ſending ſtrong deluſions upon them that receive not the love of the truth, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.10, 11. <hi>John Bunyan</hi> hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:97824:44"/>
Baptiſm, but what love he hath thereto, appears by his words; wherefore no marvel that his mind is blinded, and his underſtanding darkned, that he might believe lyes, and deceive himſelf with fallacies, as he doth in the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Reaſon, where he tells us of ſome (of his Proſelytes) that have the Doctrine of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, but do not practiſe it becauſe they want Light therein.</p>
            <p>What a Contradiction is this! if they want Light, they cannot have the Doctrine; if they have the Doctrine, they muſt have Light, ſo far as to know it; and therefore <hi>John Bunyan</hi>'s diſtinction between the Doctrine and Practice of Water-baptiſm will nothing avail. We rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily allow that, and oftentimes find that many have the Doctrine (although not without light) without the Practice, whom it ſeems are ſuch as <hi>John Bunyan</hi> is bold to have Communion with.</p>
            <p>He may well ſay, <hi>Bold,</hi> for he hath no Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-warrant for it, and it is a great boldneſs to adventure in Church-Communion beyond what is written, yea, contrary to what is written; for our Saviour ſaith, <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.47. <hi>He that knew his Lord's will</hi> (that had the Doctrine of a Duty) <hi>and prepared not himſelf</hi> (to Practiſe) <hi>neither did according to his will, ſhall be beaten with many ſtripes.</hi> And as ſuch as neglect their duty are thus threatned, ſo evil is declared to
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:97824:45"/>
perſecute thoſe that teach men ſo, and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage them therein, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.19. wherein what <hi>John Bunyan</hi> may expect I wiſh him ſeriouſly to conſider; he ſeems, <hi>pag.</hi> 122. to be conſcious to himſelf that ſome might judge him guilty thereof, whoſe mouths he would ſtop by his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quivocations, &amp;c. but at the laſt day ſuch things will ſtand in no ſtead.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 4. I come now to his fourth Reaſon, pag. 99. <hi>I am bold to hold Communion with viſible Saints, as aforeſaid (viz.</hi> unbaptized) <hi>becauſe God hath Communion with them, whoſe Example in the caſe we are ſtreightly Commanded to follow; Receive you one another as Chriſt Jeſus hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived you,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> Rom. 15.1, 6. <hi>to the Glory of God; yea, though they be Saints of Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions contrary to you; though it goeth againſt the mind of them that are ſtrong, we that are ſtrong ought to bear the infirmities of the weak:</hi> What Infirmities? (ſaith <hi>John Bunyan) Thoſe that are natural, are incident to all: they are infirmities then that are ſinful, all ſuch infirmities are laid upon Chriſt,</hi> pag. 100. <hi>wherefore, vain man, think not by the ſtreightneſs of thy order in outward and bodily conformity to outward and ſhadowiſh Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, that thy peace is maintained with God; for peace with God is by Faith in the blood of his Croſs, who hath born the reproaches and errors of you both: Thou erreſt in a Subſtance, he erreth in a Circumſtance, upon whom muſt theſe errors fall?</hi>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:97824:45"/>
pag. 101. <hi>Muſt they for this be caſt out of the Church?</hi> No: <hi>Theſe are all, yea thoſe reproaches, wherein the wiſdom of Heaven is reproached, are fallen upon Chriſt,</hi> pag. 102. <hi>wherefore God hath received him, Chriſt hath received him; wherefore do ye receive him. There is more ſolidity in this Argument, than if all the Churches of God had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived him. Will any ſay we cannot believe that God hath received any but ſuch as are baptized? I will not ſuppoſe a Brother ſo ſtupified, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to that I will not anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> In the anſwer to this long Reaſon, wherein <hi>John Bunyan</hi> hath run himſelf out of breath; Conſider firſt, That thoſe Scriptures alleaged by <hi>John Bunyan,</hi> nothing concern the matter in hand, for they were written to bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized perſons by his own Confeſſion, <hi>pag.</hi> 92. as alſo appears by the Apoſtle's words, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.3, 4.</p>
            <p>Secondly, That receiving there ſpoken of, doth not intend the receiving into Fellowſhip, (for that was already done) but a holy recepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the bowels of love, and tender-hearted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that ſo with one mind and with one mouth thy might glorifie God, <hi>Chap.</hi> 15.6. whereto they are perſwaded from the conſideration of God's bounty, and the grace of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt extended to them.</p>
            <p>Wherefore concerning unbaptized perſons (as the Apoſtle doth not ſpeak of them, or intend
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:97824:46"/>
them, in reference to Church-Communion) I might now paſs them by, as being nothing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in thoſe words of the Apoſtle afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned by <hi>John Bunyan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſince he ſo much boaſts of their Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with God, I will anſwer in the Apoſtle's words, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.12. <hi>What have I to do to judge them that are without?</hi> I ſhall leave them to the Judgment of God, to whom they muſt either ſtand or fall, only adviſing all ſuch to make their Calling and Election ſure, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.10. not truſting to <hi>John Bunyan</hi>'s words (who would ſow pillows under their arm-holes) but walk according to the Rule of the Holy Scripture; and then the Church will have Fellowſhip with them: and God hath promiſed what they ſhall bind or looſe on Earth, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18. ſhall be bound or looſed in Heaven; God himſelf hath great reſpect to his Church.</p>
            <p>But to return; If I ſhould grant that God hath Communion with many of them; is not <hi>John Bunyan</hi> ſtrangely ſtupified, as to reaſon from thence, yea to account it an Argument of ſo great ſolidity, that the Church ought there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to have Communion with them? Hath not God Communion wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h many, that the Church may not have Communion with? The Apoſtle ſpeaks, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.14. of ſome <hi>Gentiles, which ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving not the Law, were a Law unto themſelves, who did ſhew the work of the Law written in their
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:97824:46"/>
hearts:</hi> With ſuch perſons ſurely God had Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, for he did communicate that know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge to them by his holy Spirit; yet I ſuppoſe <hi>John Bunyan,</hi> conſidering his own words, <hi>p.</hi> 72. (viz. <hi>That none were to he admitted into Fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip but ſuch as were Circumciſed, nothing elſe could give the devouteſt perſon that breathed a being of memberſhip</hi>) will not ſay the Church of the <hi>Jews</hi> ought to have had Communion with them (although they had Communion with God) during their uncircumciſion.</p>
            <p>Secondly, God hath Communion with Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, <hi>whoſe Angels behold the face of our Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Father,</hi> Matth. 18.10. <hi>to whom pertaineth the Kingdom of Heaven,</hi> Mark. 10.14. Such Chriſt received; yet the Church ought not to have Communion with them before profeſſion of Faith, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>So that this ſolid Argument proves of no force; God's thoughts are unſearchable in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to himſelf; but in relation to the Church he declares his will, wherein he appears a God of Order, and not of Confuſion, and ſo it is or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained in the Churches. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.33, 40. whom although the Apoſtle exhorts, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.1. <hi>to bear one anothers infirmities;</hi> he doth not mean the denial of Baptiſm, or any other neceſſary duty (as <hi>John Bunyan</hi> wickedly pretends).</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But what infirmities then,</hi> ſaith <hi>J. Bunyan?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:97824:47"/>I anſwer, Natural infirmities, and alſo their opinion in things indifferent, which the Apoſtle was treating of, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. that either may be done, or may not be done, without ſin; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning which the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>All things are lawful,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.12. It is lawful to eat, and lawful to forbear, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.14. but touching Baptiſm, it hath already been proved a neceſſary duty, and cannot be omitted by a Chriſtian without ſin.</p>
            <p>But if ſo, <hi>John Bunyan</hi> tells you, <hi>That ſinful infirmities muſt be born with.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How <hi>John Bunyan!</hi> muſt the Church of God bear with ſin? muſt it not be reproved? Is not this the ready way to make the Houſe of God a Den of Thieves? <hi>Matth.</hi> 21.13.</p>
            <p>But ſaith <hi>John Bunyan, All ſuch infirmities are laid upon Chriſt, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer; That <hi>Chriſt bare the ſin of the world,</hi> Joh. 1.29. <hi>upon his own body on the tree,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.24. I confeſs; and alſo that <hi>by him all that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve are juſtified from all things from which they could not be juſtified by the Law of</hi> Moſes, <hi>Act.</hi> 13.39. I grant; <hi>Chriſt being ſet forth as a Propiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation (through Faith in his blood) for the remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſins that are paſt, that God might appear juſt, and the Juſtifier of him that believeth in Jeſus, Rom.</hi> 3.25, 26.</p>
            <p>But that the ſinful Infirmities of Chriſtians ſhall be ſo born by Chriſt, as to be forgiven without Confeſſion and forſaking, I do not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve;
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:97824:47"/>
               <hi>If we confeſs our ſins,</hi> ſaith <hi>John,</hi> 1 Joh. 1.10. <hi>He is faithful and juſt to forgive us our ſins; he that confeſſeth and forſaketh ſhall find mercy, Prov.</hi> 28.13. But this bearing will not ſerve <hi>John Bunyan</hi>'s turn, for. if there muſt be open confeſſion and forſaking, it is nothing to his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, it will not then bolſter up men in their diſobedience.</p>
            <p>Wherefore he is bold to affirm, <hi>That all your infirmities are fallen upon Chriſt, yea, even errors in Circumſtances, and errors in Subſtance, ſuch whereby the wiſdom of Heaven is reproached, Chriſt bears and takes away.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If <hi>John Bunyan</hi> ſaith true; here are large pillows to ſow under your arm-holes; thoſe of old, were not ſo expert as <hi>Juhn Bunyan,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they made Lyes their Refuge, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28.17. yet <hi>their bed was ſhorter, than a man could ſtretch himſelf on it; and the covering narrower, than that he could wrap himſelf in it,</hi> Iſa. 28.20. But <hi>John Bunyan</hi>'s is large enough; err in what you will, Chriſt hath born it; and the Church ought to bear with you, it ſeems; for there is no error, but it is either in <hi>circumſtance</hi> or <hi>ſubſtance.</hi> Well, be it what it will, <hi>Although you reproach the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Heaven, it is</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>born by Chriſt, and muſt be born by your Brethren.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſure his dawbing will appear to be with untempered mortar, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 13.10, 11. And if he may not be charged with that preſumption, the
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:97824:48"/>
Apoſtle tells you was in ſome, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.1. <hi>Who would ſin, that Grace may abound?</hi> yet I am ſure whil'ſt he is pleading concerning his Fellowſhip without Baptiſm, he countenanceth and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rageth all ſin, overthroweth all Church-diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline; and you may then gueſs what (if his Rule be obſerved) will become of the Church it ſelf, as further we will conſider in his repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion: <hi>Vain man</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>think not by the ſtreightneſs of thy order, &amp;c. that thy peace is main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained with God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Is not this the fruit of a ſtupified head; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, who would account, and alſo call his Brethren, <hi>vain men:</hi> and that for ſtreightneſs of Order?</p>
            <p>Is not Order to be obſerved in the Churches, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.40? and can it be too ſtrictly obſerved? ſurely No; whilſt orderly, it cannot be too ſtreight; except for <hi>John Bunyan</hi> who would not have it ſo, that his confuſed worſhip may come in the place.</p>
            <p>But then he will tell you, <hi>It is but outward and bodily conformity to outward and ſhadowiſh Circumſtances that he accounts vain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But is not outward and bodily conformity, and that to ſuch as he calls <hi>outward</hi> and <hi>ſhadow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh Circumſtances,</hi> required in a Chriſtian? He doth not only ſo account Baptiſm, but alſo <hi>breaking of Bread, the Supper of the Lord,</hi> for ſo he ſaith, <hi>pag.</hi> 64. <hi>Touching ſhadowiſh or figurative
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:97824:48"/>
Circumſtances, Chriſt hath ordained two in his Church,</hi> viz. <hi>Water-baptiſm, and the Supper of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now what Chriſtian will call it vain, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form to the Supper of the Lord (which is ſo exactly required by Chriſt himſelf)? Surely none, or few men but <hi>John Bunyan;</hi> and if con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity thereto be not vain, why muſt Baptiſm? which he confeſſeth to be of the ſame Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>pag.</hi> 64.</p>
            <p>Well, the Conformity to Chriſt's Ordinances is not in vain; <hi>The way of the Lord is ſtrength to the upright,</hi> Prov. 10.19.</p>
            <p>Yea, bodily and outward Conformity. <hi>I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you brethren</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> Rom. 12.1.) <hi>by the mercies of God, that you preſent your bodies a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Sacrifice; Glorifie God in your body,</hi> 1 Cor. 6.20. <hi>Yield the members of your bodies as inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of righteouſneſs unto God,</hi> Rom. 6.13.</p>
            <p>But it may be <hi>John Bunyan</hi> will tell me, I miſtake him, for that which he accounts vain, is for perſons to think thereby to maintain their peace with God, which is obtained by Faith in the blood of his Croſs.</p>
            <p>To which I will anſwer; That although our peace with God is by Faith, yet it is maintained by our obedience to Chriſt's Holy Ordinances, they are the things that belong to our peace, that maintain and encreaſe our peace with God, (I do not ſay God's peace with us) for with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:97824:49"/>
them there cannot be a good Conſcience to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, and then I am ſure no peace with God continued.</p>
            <p>In ſhort; the ſum of this Reaſon is not only ſafe, but blaſphemous: Firſt, <hi>Falſe;</hi> for it doth not follow that we may have Communion with men, becauſe God hath Communion with them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Blaſphemous;</hi> For, beſides what is ſaid concerning Chriſt bearing all ſin, whether in Circumſtance or Subſtance (which is appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently falſe) God is hereby made the Author of ſin; for in this Reaſon he urgeth, That the Church ought to bear with the ſinful infirmities of their Brethren; <hi>For thoſe</hi> (he ſaith) <hi>are cauſed for want of Light:</hi> And how come they to want Light? he tells you, <hi>pag.</hi> 94. <hi>It is God that creates Light, and he that with-holdeth:</hi> So that God not creating Light in their hearts, cauſeth them to err, and to be guilty of ſinful infirmities.</p>
            <p>Is not here verified what is written, <hi>God ſhall ſend them ſtrong deluſions to believe a lye?</hi> Is not this according to the words of that idle Servant, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.24. who ſaith of God, he knew him to be an hard man, <hi>reaping where thou haſt not ſown, and gathering where thou haſt not ſtrawed?</hi> So ſaith <hi>John Bunyan;</hi> who without Repentance may expect the like ſentence.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:97824:49"/>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 5. I come now to his 5th Reaſon, <hi>p.</hi> 104. <hi>Becauſe a failer in ſuch a Circumſtance as Water, doth not unchriſtian us: This muſt needs be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, not only from what was ſaid before, but for that thouſands of thouſands that could not conſent thereto, are now with the innumerable company of Angels, &amp;c. wherefore what is ſaid of eating, or the contrary, may as to this be ſaid of Water-baptiſm; neither if I am baptized, am I the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; neither if I be not, am I the worſe: not the better before God, nor the worſe before Men: Whereupon</hi> (after ſome plauſible words, he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes, <hi>pag.</hi> 106.) <hi>ſeeing the things wherein we exceed each other, are ſuch as neither make nor mar Chriſtianity; let us love one another, and walk to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether according to the glorious Rule above ſpecified,</hi> (meaning to have Church-Communion with unbaptized perſons.)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> To love one another, I ſhould readily conſent, for we ought to love all men: But for Church-Communion I cannot, until I ſee it proved that we ought to do ſo, which I am ſure <hi>John Bunyan</hi> hath not; for he hath not yet pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved it lawful, much leſs expedient, but further from being neceſſary, which he pretends. And ſurely this Reaſon cannot ſway a wiſe man, to do that which is not proved lawful; I ſay, this Reaſon which is grounded upon a falſe Poſition: for although Baptiſm doth not make a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, yet the want of it may mar a Chriſtian, and
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:97824:50"/>
the neglect thereof unchriſtian men. <hi>For he that deſpiſeth God</hi> (although once honoured) <hi>ſhall be lightly eſteemed,</hi> 1 Sam. 2.30. A good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience may be put away, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.19. that there may be need of the formation of Chriſt in the heart again, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.19.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>John Bunyan</hi>'s inſtance <hi>of the thouſand thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands that did not conſent to Baptiſm, which are now</hi> (as he ſaith) <hi>in Heaven,</hi> is no ſufficient proof that it ought to be, or that it may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed now. I ſuppoſe he will confeſs there are thouſand thouſands as much in Heaven as they, who did not believe that Chriſt was then come in the fleſh; but he that denieth it now is Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.3. And notwithſtanding <hi>John Bunyan</hi>'s confidence, if he ſhould now deny Chriſt come in the fleſh, it would unchriſtian him.</p>
            <p>I might give many more inſtances in this caſe, but from hence you may perceive how inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate he is, to conclude that of Baptiſm, (from falſe grounds) which <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh of eating meats, which were lawful to be eaten, or not eaten: Would any wiſe man oppoſe ſuch indifferent things, to an Ordinance and Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Chriſt Jeſus? ſure Obedience to expreſs Commands, whatſoever we are before men, makes us better before God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ</hi> 6. I come now to his 6th Reaſon, <hi>p.</hi> 107. <hi>I am therefore for holding Communion thus, becauſe
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:97824:50"/>
the Edification of Souls, in the Faith and Holineſs of the Goſpel, is of greater concernment, than our agreeing in, or conteſting for the buſineſs of Water-baptiſm: That the Edification of the Soul is of the greateſt concern, is out of meaſure evident, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw. John Bunyan</hi>'s Poſition here ſtated, he endeavoureth by divers Reaſons to prove, (viz. <hi>That the Edification of the Soul is of the greateſt concern,</hi>) which I here omit, becauſe whilſt he endeavoureth to prove that, he mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes the matter in queſtion; for it is apparent that Baptiſm, and the reſt of Chriſt's Ordinances, are the means appointed for the Edification of the Souls of men; and if ſo, the Argument is fallacious and muſt fall; which ſurely he is himſelf conſcious of, and therefore to prevent it, he ſaith, <hi>pag.</hi> 109. <hi>Know that the Edification of the Church of God dependeth not upon, neither is tyed to this or that Circumſtance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Much ſaid, but little proved; wherefore in ſhort I may anſwer, You have only <hi>J. Bunyan</hi>'s word for it, who, herein doth not only exclude Baptiſm, but alſo whatſoever he is pleaſed to call a Circumſtance, whereof the Supper of the Lord is one by his own confeſſion, <hi>pag.</hi> 64. ſo that it alſo is excluded (by him) from Church-Edification, contrary to what is declared of the Primitive Saints, who walking in the fear of God, having Fellowſhip one with another, were edified: yea, <hi>Paul</hi> accounts Church-diſcipline
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:97824:51"/>
for the Edification of the Church, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.10. And in truth all Goſpel-Ordinances are for Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication; ſo that if we muſt preſs after that, it obligeth us to preſs after the means tending thereto.</p>
            <p>But <hi>J. Bunyan</hi> ſeems to put a little gloſs upon the matter, <hi>viz. When there is in the hearts of the Godly different perſwaſions about it, then it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh them in the wiſdom of God to take more care for their peace and unity, than to widen their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfortable differences.</hi> Thus <hi>J. Bunyan</hi> would have the Churches to be like <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi,</hi> Brethren agreeing in iniquity; to bear with ſin, and to wink at the trangreſſions of Chriſt's Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, (rather than to diſagree thereupon): contrary to the advice of the Apoſtle, who (as he withſtood <hi>Peter</hi> to the face, becauſe he was to be blamed, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.11.) directs, <hi>That if any Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther walketh diſorderly (viz.</hi> in diſobedience to Chriſt's Ordinances) <hi>he muſt be withdrawn from,</hi> 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3.6.</p>
            <p>But <hi>John Bunyan,</hi> to perſwade the Churches to ſtrike hands in diſobedience, and to counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance their doings therein; alleageth, <hi>pag.</hi> 110, divers inſtances of unlawful things done of old, yet winked at, if not approved.</p>
            <p>To all which (if it be ſo) ſure the Apoſtle's words <hi>(Rom.</hi> 6.1. <hi>What ſhall we ſay thereto? ſhall we continue in ſin that grace may abound?
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:97824:51"/>
God forbid:)</hi> might (to ſober men) be a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient anſwer.</p>
            <p>But that I might diſcharge my duty herein, I ſhall give (for the better ſatisfaction of thoſe concerned) a particular Anſwer thereto in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</p>
            <p>His firſt Inſtance is of <hi>Aaron,</hi> pag. 109. in theſe words, <hi>Although</hi> Aaron <hi>tranſgreſſed the Law, becauſe he eat not the Sin-Offering of the People, yet ſeeing he could not do it with ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to his own Conſcience,</hi> Moſes <hi>was content that he left it undone,</hi> Levit. 10.16.20.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw. John Bunyan</hi> tells us, That <hi>Aaron</hi> tranſgreſſed the Law, becauſe the Law was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Conſcience, and that <hi>Moſes</hi> was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent therewith; but ſurely then, <hi>Moſes</hi> was not faithful in all things as a Servant, <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.5. For the ſame Apoſtle tells us, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.2. That <hi>the Law was ſo ſtedfaſt, that every tranſgreſſion and diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience received a juſt recompence of reward:</hi> which muſt needs be falſe if <hi>John Bunyan</hi> ſaith true; for he ſaith <hi>Aaron tranſgreſsed,</hi> yet <hi>Moſes was content:</hi> ſure it was great preſumption in him to tollerate what the Law of God forbad: But the Text alleaged, doth not ſay <hi>Aaron</hi> tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed the Law; neither doth it ſay, the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of the Law was againſt his Conſcience, theſe are but <hi>John Bunyan</hi>'s fancies: All that the Text ſaith is, <hi>That Moſes was angry when he found the Sin-Offering burnt,</hi> and ſaith, <hi>Wherefore
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:97824:52"/>
have ye not eaten it in the holy place?</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Aaron</hi> anſwers, <hi>It was Offered by the People this day wherein ſuch things have befaln me, that if I had eaten, would it have been accepted?</hi> Which anſwer when <hi>Moſes</hi> heard he was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, for therein the Law was not broken, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was the performance thereof againſt <hi>Aaron</hi>'s Conſcience.</p>
            <p>The ſum therefore of the matter is this; God, who took great care for his People, did Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand that <hi>Aaron</hi> and his Sons ſhould eat ſuch parts of the Offerings of the People as he di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected, <hi>viz.</hi> it was their due by the Law of God, ſo that they might eat thereof, what nature re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, (they were not enjoyned to eat all, or ſo much) the reſt, <hi>viz.</hi> what they left, was to be burnt.</p>
            <p>And in the caſe before alleaged, it ſeems <hi>Aaron</hi> eat none, but burnt all: whereupon <hi>Moſes</hi> apprehending it to be in contempt of God's Law (as <hi>Joſhua</hi> thought of the erection of the Altar, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 22.) was angry with them, but yet enquiring into the cauſe wherefore they did not eat it, <hi>Aaron</hi> tells him, That it was the day wherein he loſt his two Sons, (<hi>verſ.</hi> 2.) and therefore he could not eat it, neither did he think it would be acceptable if he had; which when <hi>Moſes</hi> heard, he was content, knowing thereby that eating in general was not denyed by <hi>Aaron,</hi> or againſt his Conſcience, as <hi>John
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:97824:52"/>
Bunyan</hi> falſly pretends; but that the occaſion then required his forbearance: and therefore this is nothing to the purpoſe in hand, it is no more than if a Chriſtian (owning the Supper of the Lord as a truth to be obſerved), ſhould once at the Celebration thereof (being it may be under ſome trouble or diſcontent) abſent himſelf; or if upon ſome ſpecial occaſion Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm ſhould be deferred for ſome hours, who would find fault with this? which was <hi>Aaron</hi>'s caſe.</p>
            <p>His ſecond Inſtance is, <hi>pag.</hi> 110. concerning <hi>Eldad</hi> and <hi>Medad, Who</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>Joſhua was ſo zealous againſt, becauſe they Propheſied in the Camp, without firſt going to the door of the Tabernacle as they were Commanded, that he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired</hi> Moſes <hi>to forbid them,</hi> Numb. 11.16, 26. <hi>But</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>Moſes calls his zeal, envie; praying for more ſuch Prophets: knowing although they failed in a Circumſtance, they were right in that which was better; for the Edification of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the Camp was that which pleaſed</hi> Moſes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> What will not People do when they endeavour to fight againſt the Laws of Chriſt? If <hi>Moſes</hi> did account <hi>Joſhua</hi>'s zeal envy, much more may it truly be ſaid of <hi>John Bunyan,</hi> that his zeal herein produceth envy: I might in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to this Inſtance alleage, what <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith of the falſe Apoſtles that preached Chriſt out of envy; yet <hi>Paul</hi> rejoyced that Chriſt was prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched:
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:97824:53"/>
And would it not be thought ſtrange that any ſhould collect from hence that their act was lawful, becauſe <hi>Paul</hi> rejoyced therein, when as many times good is produced by evil acts?</p>
            <p>But further, <hi>Eldad</hi> and <hi>Medad</hi> in their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſying did nothing contrary to Law, they were not forbidden to Prophecy, nor that it ſhould be done in the Camp, but on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, God's Spirit came upon them there, and thereby they were induced to propheſy; and ſo it is nothing to the purpoſe for which it is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaged by <hi>John Bunyan,</hi> unleſs he can ſhew us any incited by God's Spirit to neglect Baptiſm.</p>
            <p>But if you ſay, <hi>They ought to have went to the door of the Tabernacle?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer, That it was not expreſs duty to be performed on their parts, but for the manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God's ſelecting them to govern the People, which in a holy modeſty they eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chewed.</p>
            <p>But then in the next place, <hi>John Bunyan</hi> gives you a third Inſtance, <hi>pag.</hi> 110. <hi>That in</hi> Heze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah's <hi>time, although the People came to the Paſſeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver in an undue manner, and did eat it otherwiſe than it was written, yet the wiſe King would not forbid them, but rather admitted it, knowing that their Edification was of greater Concern than to hold them to a Circumſtance or two,</hi> 2 Chron. 30.13, 27. <hi>Yea God himſelf did like the wiſdom of the King, and healed, that is, forgave the People at the
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:97824:53"/>
Prayer of</hi> Hezekiah: <hi>And obſerve</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>notwithſtanding this diſorder as to Circumſtances, the Feaſt was kept with great gladneſs,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> What now, <hi>John Bunyan,</hi> how great a labyrinth haſt thou brought us into (if thy words be true) muſt that be admitted in the Church? yea, doth God himſelf like it, even that which is undue, yea contrary to what is written? Sure we are left herein (if this be ſo) to every man's fancy; who is there that will not pretend the Edification of the People in all their Concerns? and how ſhall we controul them? For, <hi>Quot homines tot ſententiae,</hi> the Scripture muſt not be our Judge, <hi>For that may be admitted,</hi> ſaith <hi>John Bunyan, yea, well liked by God, which is contrary to what is written:</hi> This he further confirms, <hi>pag.</hi> 101. <hi>For all things</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>even Laws themſelves muſt give place to the Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication and Profit of God's People.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Surely <hi>John Bunyan</hi> doth not eſteem that his God was wiſe enough; when he made Laws, as to foreſee what would be for his Peoples pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit and Edification.</p>
            <p>But as he doth herein deprave the wiſdom of God; ſo he is contrary to himſelf. For he ſaith in another place, <hi>pag.</hi> 45. <hi>I believe that Jeſus Chriſt by the word of the Scriptures, will judge all men at the day of Doom.</hi> Now this cannot be, if the Word of the Scriptures, and the Laws therein contained, muſt give place to a preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:97824:54"/>
Edification of the People; would not that (<hi>viz.</hi> to plead the Edification of the People) if his words be true, be a good excuſe at the day of Doom?</p>
            <p>But I hope no man will be ſo unwiſe as to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve him, who is not only ſo contrary to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, but to the holy Apoſtle, who deſired the Godly (by the Example of himſelf and the reſt of the Apoſtles) to learn not ſo much as to think above that which is written, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.6. and ſo much the rather, becauſe he knew that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards there would ariſe ſuch preſumptuous perſons as <hi>John Bunyan,</hi> who would pretend they might do otherwiſe (even contrary to the written Law of God) that good might come; Concerning whom <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.8. <hi>Their damnation is juſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But perhaps you will ſay with <hi>John Bunyan, Was it not ſo in</hi> Hezekiah<hi>'s time? Did they not keep the Paſſeover otherwiſe than it was written, and yet allowed?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer, <hi>No:</hi> There was no allowance of any thing contrary to what was written in the Law; wherefore, firſt, we muſt note concerning the time, there was a limitation by the Law of God; as appears, <hi>Numb.</hi> 9.9, 10, 11. <hi>The Lord ſpake unto</hi> Moſes <hi>ſaying: If any of you, or your poſterity, be unclean, or in a journey afar off, that he cannot keep the Paſſeover in its appointed ſeaſon, they ſhall keep it on the fourteenth day of the ſecond
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:97824:54"/>
month at Even, &amp;c.</hi> which was the time that <hi>Hezekiah</hi> (taking Counſel by the Law of God) kept it, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 30.2, 3, 16. uncleanneſs and diſtance of place, not permitting the obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof in the firſt month, which was the time at firſt appointed, and that (although a Circumſtance) ſo exactly, that God threatned death to the man that ſhould neglect the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed ſeaſon, <hi>Numb.</hi> 9.13. And it is apparent what befel <hi>Jeroboam</hi> for his Error therein; 1 <hi>King.</hi> 12.23. Although he was as ready as <hi>John Bunyan</hi> to plead the Edification and eaſe of the People for his warrant, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 12.28.</p>
            <p>But if now any ſay, <hi>Why did the King pray God to pardon, if there was not an undue manner in the eating? And why is the Lord ſaid to heal the People if they did not offend?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which I anſwer, Firſt, That the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the Paſſeover in reſpect to the time when it was kept as aforeſaid, was not undue: Nor, Secondly, any thing that the King either Commanded, or Allowed, yet there was an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due receiving the Paſſeover otherwiſe than what was written: But how was that? the Text declareth, That there was an intruſion of many of the People who had not cleanſed themſelves according to the Law, which although <hi>John Bunyan</hi> pretends the King did allow, <hi>(knowing that their Edification was of greater concern than to hold them to a Circumſtance or two)</hi> the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:97824:55"/>
ſaith the contrary, <hi>viz. That</hi> Hezekiah <hi>did account it a ſin</hi> (and not at all for Edification or Profit) and therefore <hi>prayed earneſtly to God for pardon</hi> (leſt that therefore his anger ſhould break forth againſt them); unto whom the Lord was pleaſed graciouſly to hearken, and healed them: From whence <hi>John Bunyan</hi> wickedly concludes that God did like it; and thereupon urgeth it as a great Reaſon why now the Church ſhould bear with undue proceedings, contrary to what is written. But, well did the Holy Ghoſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend ſuch, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.1. that becauſe God was gracious in pardoning, they would preſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly ſin that grace might abound, which ought to be abhorred by all the Godly.</p>
            <p>But methinks ſome will ſay, <hi>John Bunyan</hi> offers further in this matter, <hi>pag.</hi> 101. viz. <hi>When Chriſt's Diſciples plucked the ears of Corn, and were charged by the Phariſees with breach of the Sabbath,</hi> Matth. 12.1, 6. <hi>Their Lord excuſeth them, and rebuketh their Adverſaries; ſaying, Have ye not read what</hi> David <hi>did when he was an hungred, and they that were with him, how he entred into the Houſe of God and did eat the Shewbread, which was not lawful for him to eat, neither for them that were with him, but only for the Prieſts? Or, have you not read in the Law, how that on the Sabbath-day, the Prieſts in the Temple, prophane the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath and are blameleſs: Why blameleſs</hi> ſaith <hi>John Bunyan?) becauſe they did it in order to the Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:97824:55"/>
of the People;</hi> From whence he concludes, <hi>If Laws and Ordinances have been broken, and the breach of them born with, when the profit and edification of the People came in competition, how much more may we have Church-Communion where no Law is tranſgreſſed thereby?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yes ſurely; For <hi>where there is no Law, there is no Tranſgreſſion;</hi> there cannot be in that any ſin.</p>
            <p>But <hi>John Bunyan</hi> hath forgot in his Concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the matter in hand, which is not whether we may have Church-Communion where no Law is tranſgreſſed: (which he needed not have taken ſuch pains to prove) but whether we may have Church-Communion with perſons not obedient to Baptiſm, which before hath been often proved a Command, yea, a neceſſary Command, and confeſſed by himſelf to belong to all Diſciples, (and ſo alſo undoubtedly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended by him in this Reaſon) according to the written Word, wherefore he pleadeth for doing otherwiſe than it was written; and doth tell you (but how truly you may judge) <hi>Laws and Ordinances have been broken, and the breach of them born with, when the profit of the People and their edification came in competition;</hi> which it ſeems <hi>John Bunyan</hi> prefers before the honour of God: when he conceits there may be Profit and Edification, he will break even Laws and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances to carry on his deſign; to whom verily
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:97824:56"/>
it will one day be ſaid, <hi>Who hath required this at your hand?</hi> Iſa. 1.12. to break my Laws for your own profit? When you did pretend to worſhip me, did not you ſerve your ſelves, <hi>Zech.</hi> 7.6. yea, although it reached to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of my Laws? You will, it ſeems, <hi>make them give place</hi> (to uſe <hi>John Bunyan</hi>'s own words) for the advancing of your ſelves.</p>
            <p>Will not this (in a wiſe man's judgment) be hard to be anſwered, when the God of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſhall plead in the defence of his holy Laws: the Diſciples plucking the ears of Corn will not juſtifie it; for know, that was no ſin upon the account of any Law of God, they might eat, yea, take their food on the Sabbath day, there was no illegality therein.</p>
            <p>But if here you ask, <hi>Why Chriſt did not tell the Phariſees ſo?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer, That he knowing the hardneſs of their hearts, endeavoured rather to convince them, by the inſtances of ſuch things as were allowed by themſelves: As <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Atheni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> Act. 17. alleageth the ſayings of their own Poets: So doth Chriſt here, yet not allowing any diſobedience; no not in the Prieſts, who <hi>John Bunyan</hi> is pleaſed to ſay were <hi>blameleſs,</hi> becauſe they did it in order to the Edification of the People.</p>
            <p>But I will ſay they were <hi>blameleſs,</hi> becauſe they did it in order to the Law of God, <hi>Numb.</hi>
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:97824:56"/>
28.9. which required the Offerings to be made on the Sabbath day; ſo that although the act conſidered ſimply, <hi>viz.</hi> the ſlaying the Offering, &amp;c. was a prophanation of the Sabbath, yet in that it was the Offering-Sacrifice, they were blameleſs, as aforeſaid, becauſe God (the great Law-giver) required it, as our Saviour gives us the like inſtance of the Circumciſing a man on the Sabbath day, which in that it was God's Command to be done on the Eighth day, was no breach of the Sabbath when it happened to be then done.</p>
            <p>As for the inſtance of <hi>David,</hi> although I might ſay ſomething in the caſe, ſeeing our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour doth not juſtifie it, but ſaith it was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful, I ſhall conclude that the like may be ſaid of <hi>John Bunyan</hi>'s Church-Communion, that he doth and teacheth that which is not lawful to be done; wherefore at his peril it will be for teaching men to break Chriſt's Commands, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.19. although Edification be his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 7. Wherein now leaving him, I come to his 7th Reaſon, <hi>viz. Therefore I am for holding Communion thus, becauſe Love, which above all things we are commanded to put on, is of much more worth than to break about Baptiſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the ſubſtance of this Reaſon, although many words are uſed therein to no purpoſe;
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:97824:57"/>
wherefore I will in ſhort anſwer, That I confeſs Love to be an eminent duty; it would be too tedious for me to ſet forth the <hi>Encomiums</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, I wiſh heartily that it was more found a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Saints; Concerning whom, I pray God their Love may abound yet more and more.</p>
            <p>But let me tell <hi>John Bunyan,</hi> Love hath its boundaries, and marks of demonſtration<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> wherefore herein I ſhall ſay with the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.2, 3. <hi>By this we know that we love the Children of God, when we love God and keep its Commandments; for this is the love of God, that we keep his Commandments.</hi> Otherwiſe (what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever we pretend) we neither love God, nor the Children of God: for as love to God, ſo love to the Children of God, is inconſiſtent with diſobedience to God's Commands.</p>
            <p>Wherefore to <hi>John Bunyan</hi>'s pretence, <hi>viz. That Love is of much more worth than Baptiſm, and that we are Commanded above all things to put it on.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I muſt tell him, it is of more worth than Faith, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13, 13. and if above all things, thou above Faith to be put on, yet I ſuppoſe <hi>John Bunyan</hi> will not allow in this caſe Church-Communion without Faith, which may as well be urged from this Reaſon; but herein, as in all, a Preacher of the Goſpel, ſhould learn
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:97824:57"/>
rightly to divide the Word of Truth; the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is not only demonſtrated, but preſerved many times by that which is leſſer, as Life by food, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 8. But <hi>John Bunyan</hi> in his 8th Reaſon, <hi>pag.</hi> 119. would have you know, <hi>That for God's People to divide into parties, or ſhut each other from Church-Communion, though in greater Points, and higher pretences than this of Water-baptiſm, hath heretofore been counted carnal, and the actors therein Babiſh-Chriſtians,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I confeſs this looks more like an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of weight, than any heretofore alleaged; For, if this be true, he ſaith ſomething to the purpoſe: for it muſt be granted, that what was in the Primitive Churches accounted Carnal, muſt ſo be accounted now: But, <hi>Praiſe a fair day at night. The end tryeth all things.</hi> I am ſure that to ſhut out of Communion for the neglect of Baptiſm was never accounted Carnal, for in thoſe dayes, by <hi>John Bunyan</hi>'s Confeſſion, <hi>pag.</hi> 91. Water-baptiſm went before Church-Communion, and therefore according to this Argument it ought to do ſo now.</p>
            <p>But he ſaith, That <hi>to ſhut out of Communion upon greater Points, and higher pretences than
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:97824:58"/>
Water-baptiſm, was then reckoned Carnal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But by <hi>John Bunyan</hi>'s favour, it is untrue; The Apoſtle himſelf commanded to <hi>withdraw from every Brother that walketh diſorderly, not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their traditions,</hi> 2 Theſſ. 3.6. To ſhut ſuch out of Communion it ſeems was not Carnality, but according to the mind of God's holy Spirit; and thoſe that deny Baptiſm, are guilty of that diſorder, as hath been already proved; yea, it muſt be ſo; for <hi>John Bunyan</hi> confeſſeth, <hi>pag.</hi> 123. That <hi>Baptiſm is an holy Ordinance,</hi> which to neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect and deſpiſe, is diſorder and unholineſs, and the perſons guilty thereof, therefore to be ſhun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            <p>But <hi>John Bunyan,</hi> to confirm his aſſertion, tells you, That <hi>Paul, Apollo, Cephas, and Chriſt, were doubtleſs higher things than thoſe about which we contend; yet when they made diviſions about them, they were ſharply rebuked.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But as his Falſhood, ſo his Craft is diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered; For that diviſion in <hi>Corinth,</hi> was not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout higher things than Baptiſm, neither did it extend to breach of Communion. As for <hi>Paul, Apollo, Cephas,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt,</hi> they were neither of them denyed, there was no higher Points in Queſtion, neither (as to their diviſion) are they charged with the denyal of any Doctrine, or any practice in Worſhip.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:97824:58"/>But their caſe was thus; they were it ſeems puffed up with pride and ſtrove for ſuperiority, wherein they took advantage by the eminency of their Miniſters, who had been converſant a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them; As the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> at this day ſaith, I am of <hi>Cephas,</hi> and thereupon chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lengeth the Primacy; ſo they ſaid, ſome were of <hi>Paul,</hi> ſome of <hi>Apollo,</hi> and ſome of <hi>Christ,</hi> which in truth the Apoſtle ſharply reprehends; but if either of them had been denyed, and the Church had called ſuch a perſon to accompt for his denyal, and (if perſiſting therein) ſhut him out of Communion, this would not have been accounted Carnal proceeding, although <hi>John Bunyan</hi> is pleaſed further to ſay, <hi>Let</hi> Paul, Cephas; <hi>or</hi> Chriſt <hi>himſelf be the burden of thy ſong, yet the heart from whence they flow is Carnal, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I hope he doth not mean that the heart is car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, that obeyeth the Doctrine of <hi>Paul, Cephas,</hi> or <hi>Christ,</hi> or that ſeparateth from a perſon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying <hi>Paul, Cephas,</hi> or <hi>Chriſt;</hi> this would be too great preſumption, whereof when I would clear him in my thoughts, (or, to prevent it) he appears guilty of great wickedneſs, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudence; for he is bold to ſay, <hi>pag.</hi> 120. <hi>Let the cry be never ſo loud, Chriſt, Order, the Rule, the Command, or the like, Carnality is the bottom, and they are but babies that do it.</hi> Here <hi>John
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:97824:59"/>
Bunyan</hi> leaves out, <hi>Paul, Apollo,</hi> and <hi>Cephas,</hi> and well he may, if it be but carnality and childiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to follow Chriſt, Order, the Rule, or the Commands.</p>
            <p>I wonder what <hi>John Bunyan</hi> would have us follow, or who would he have us ſeparate from, or what muſt we reſpect? if neither Chriſt, Order, the Rule, or a command be any thing with him; what, muſt fancy hear the ſway a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all, which many times is groſly ſtupified; and verily it is ſo in <hi>John Bunyan,</hi> otherwiſe he would not have ſpoken thus: And alſo further to add, That the great diviſion at <hi>Corinth</hi> was helped forward by Water-baptiſm, telling you the Apoſtle intimates as much, when he ſaith, <hi>Were ye baptized in the Name of</hi> Paul?</p>
            <p>Who would have thought to have heard ſuch unſound ſpeeches, ſuch perverſe words from one that acknowledgeth Baptiſm to be an holy Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of Chriſt? Is it likely diviſions ſhould be helped forward by an holy Ordinance? doth <hi>Paul</hi> intimate the ſame? nay, he doth urge the contrary, even by the aforeſaid words; for when the <hi>Corinthians</hi> being puffed up with pride, and ſeeking for ſuperiority, one preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to be of <hi>Paul,</hi> and another of <hi>Apollo: Paul</hi> ſeeks to diſwade them thencefrom, and
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:97824:59"/>
to convince them of their folly: He propounds theſe Queſtions; <hi>viz.</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>Is Chriſt divided?</l>
                  <l>Was <hi>Paul</hi> Crucified for you? <hi>Or,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Were you baptized in the Name of <hi>Paul?</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>John Bunyan</hi> might as well have ſaid, the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion was helped forward by Chriſt: There is as much to that purpoſe intimated in thoſe words, <hi>Is Chriſt divided?</hi> as in theſe, <hi>Were ye baptized in the Name of</hi> Paul? But the truth is, <hi>Paul</hi> endeavoured to put them in mind that there is but one Chriſt, that neither himſelf, <hi>Apollo,</hi> or <hi>Cephas,</hi> were Crucified for them: And alſo one Baptiſm, they were not baptized into the Name of any but Chriſt; wherefore he exhorts them to leave off their folly and pride, and walk in love as they were comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, but not to ſlight Baptiſm, as <hi>John Bunyan</hi> (whoſe tongue hath no bounds) is pleaſed to ſay <hi>Paul</hi> did, making no matter at all thereof in reſpect to Church-Communion. But I wiſh he may be aſhamed of his thus wreſting the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and the intentions of the Apoſtle, who alwayes ſpake reverently with an holy eſtimati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Baptiſm; not like <hi>John Bunyan,</hi> who in a little <hi>Treatiſe</hi> both commends and depraves it,
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:97824:60"/>
thereby rendring himſelf conſpicuous for his inſtability.</p>
            <p>But if you ask why the Apoſtle ſpake after that manner, ſaying, <hi>I thank God I baptized none but</hi> Criſpus <hi>and</hi> Gaius, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Know, it was not becauſe he made no mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thereof as to Church-Communion, but to take away the occaſion of their contention, as he declares himſelf, leſt any ſhould ſay, <hi>I bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized in my own Name.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And whereas <hi>John Bunyan</hi> ſeems to take ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage at thoſe words, <hi>I know not whether I baptized any other;</hi> And from thence concludes (contrary to the Apoſtles thoughts) <hi>That he did not heed who were baptized by any body; as much as if he ſhould ſay, that he did not heed whether they were baptized or no.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I muſt anſwer; That I wonder any wiſe man ſhould urge ſuch a Concluſion from <hi>Paul</hi>'s words<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> eſpecially <hi>John Bunyan,</hi> who confeſſeth Baptiſm is an holy Ordinance, and was obeyed by the <hi>Corinthians:</hi> and if ſo, <hi>Paul</hi> muſt needs know they were all baptized, and then no mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by whom, <hi>viz.</hi> which of the Apoſtles: But to take away that occaſion of boaſting con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:97824:60"/>
himſelf, he tells them he did not know whether he baptized any but the perſons afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named; which is no ſtrange thing for a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter to be ignorant of; for unleſs he keep't a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſter, how ſhould he remember it? There be ſome in our dayes that dare not ſlight Baptiſm touching Church-Communion, yet can ſay in this caſe, as <hi>Paul</hi> did.</p>
            <p>Further; whereas it is alleaged that <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, <hi>I was not ſent to Baptize, but to Preach.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Know, herein he did not ſlight Baptiſm, but placed it in its due ſtation; That <hi>Paul</hi> was ſent to baptize, is evident; for he tells you whom he did baptize; and if he had no Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion for it, then it may be truly ſaid, he bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized in his own Name: But he intends that he was not principally ſent to Baptize, but to Preach, as he ſaith in another caſe, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.14. <hi>The Man was not deceived, but the Woman:</hi> Whence you have the ſame terms, which muſt be underſtood, <hi>the Man was not primarily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, but the Woman</hi> (as the Text ſaith) <hi>was firſt in the tranſgreſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the next place <hi>John Bunyan</hi> begins to flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and tells you, <hi>He would not teach men to break the leaſt of God's Commands, and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:97824:61"/>
therein Baptiſm to be an holy Ordinance<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> pag. 123. <hi>A duty enjoyned to ſuch as receive the Goſpel,</hi> pag. 122. <hi>But it is the abuſe thereof,</hi> he ſaith, (wherein he himſelf is apparently guilty) <hi>that he complains againſt;</hi> and therein forgets himſelf, and ſaith, (without any ground or truth) <hi>What is Baptiſm? Baptiſm is nothing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What, <hi>John Bunyan!</hi> A holy Ordinance, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing! an enjoyned Duty, nothing! Where are we now?</p>
            <p>He anſwers, <hi>pag.</hi> 124. <hi>That it is no ſtrange thing, for God cryed out againſt his own Inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons when abuſed by the People,</hi> Iſa. 1.11, 12. <hi>To what purpoſe is the multitude of your Sacrifices, &amp;c. ſaith the Lord?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> But is not this <hi>John Bunyan</hi>'s blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, or at leaſt his crafty endeavours to inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate his own opinion? Did ever God cry out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his own Inſtitutions? againſt his own Appointments? No: verily the complaint was againſt the People, that they performed ſuch things contrary to God's Inſtitutions; and therefore it is not as <hi>J. Bunyan</hi> preſumes to ſay, that the Ordinances are nothing; but to what purpoſe are they? they are vain, and why ſo? becauſe not performed according to the Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:97824:61"/>
wherefore the Lord adds, <hi>Who hath requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red theſe things at your hands?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It muſt be known that God appoints the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the performance as well as the matter, yea, the qualifications of the perſons perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it; whereof if any be wanting, we ſwerve from God's Inſtitution; wherein I will ſay of Baptiſm, that although it is a neceſſary duty, yet if it be not accompanied with ſuch qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations as God requires, it profits not, it is in vain. So alſo may be ſaid of Faith, which without works is dead, <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.20. yet verily it would be ſtrange preſumption for a man to ſay in general, Faith is nothing; yea, if thoſe <hi>Iſraelites</hi> whom <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſpeaks of, had walked honeſtly as to men (which it ſeems they did not) and denyed the offering Sacrifices, the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the Sabbath, and the appointed Feaſt: I appeal to all ſober Chriſtians whether therein they would have been blameleſs; No ſure: God often puniſheth for the neglect of thoſe Inſtitutions, and therefore I ſhall conclude the anſwer to this Reaſon, with our Saviour's words, <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.23. <hi>Theſe things you ought to do, and not to leave the other undone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I come now to his 9th Reaſon, <hi>pag.</hi> 125. which is this, <hi>viz. If we ſhall reject viſible Saints
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:97824:62"/>
by calling Saints that have Communion with God, that have received the Law at the hand of Chriſt, that are of holy Converſation amongſt men, they deſiring to have Communion with us, as much as in us lyeth; we take from them their priviledges, and the bleſſings to which they are born of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Oh man full of all ſubtilty, how long wilt thou labour to deceive! Can a man (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering what hath been ſaid) be a viſible Saint, that denyeth Chriſt's Holy Ordinances? Can we be aſſured that a man hath Communion with God, who rejects his Counſel? Can a man be ſaid to receive the Law at the hands of Chriſt, that denyeth his Inſtitutions, and lives in diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to a Duty enjoyned? Can they truly deſire Communion, that refuſe to obey Baptiſm when required? What <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith to the <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians,</hi> and other Saints, is nothing to our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent purpoſe, for they were all baptized by your own confeſſion: And what you ſay afterwards concerning the Supper is as little, unleſs you could prove that unbaptized perſons have right thereto, and ought to participate thereof; which when you do, you may peradventure have a further anſwer.</p>
            <p>Touching what you ſay further in this <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> ſtuffed with Eighteen Fancies of your own
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:97824:62"/>
brain, I think a wiſe man will not judge me ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to anſwer in particular: Wherefore I will only ſay, That it ſeems like the deſign of <hi>Baalam,</hi> who (of old) was intended to curſe <hi>Iſrael;</hi> only herein appears a difference, God met <hi>Baalam</hi> of old and forbade him, thereby re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraining his purpoſed deſigns. But it ſeems as if God hath given this man over, to belch out the fruit of his own imaginations, that in him might be verified the prediction of our Saviour, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.11. <hi>They ſhall ſpeak all manner of evil againſt you falſly for my Name's ſake:</hi> Which to effect, he is bold to affirm, <hi>That Chriſtians have been the cauſe of all the Judgments we have felt, and do groan under.</hi> It is no new thing, the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens of old were of the ſame mind, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by raiſed the Primitive perſecutions: and we ſee the Devil playeth the ſame Game now: whereto I ſhall only ſay in the words of <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chael,</hi> Jud. 9. <hi>The Lord rebuke thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I come now to his 10th and laſt Reaſon, <hi>pag.</hi> 128. <hi>Which is grounded partly upon the thoughts of the World, and partly upon a ſuppoſed Condeſcention, ſo far as to commit our Souls to the Miniſtry of unbaptized perſons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereto I ſhall anſwer; As to the firſt, We ought to obey God, rather than to pleaſe men,
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:97824:63"/>
               <hi>Act.</hi> 4.19. And as to the ſecond, I ſay, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> we commit our Souls to ſuch perſons, we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> then have Communion with them: But at preſent I ſhall offer <hi>John Bunyan</hi>'s own words, <hi>pag.</hi> 133. <hi>It muſt be the prudence of every Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, to preſerve its own unity in peace and truth, and not to ſuffer ſuch confounded Doctrines, as eat out the bowels of a Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore <hi>John Bunyan</hi> and his Doctrine ought to be exploded, as a detected Gangrene encreaſing unto more ungodlineſs, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.18. For which purpoſe let us obſerve the Apoſtles advice, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.21. <hi>Try all things, and hold faſt that which is good.</hi> The God of Heaven teach us by his Holy Spirit, to try thoſe things that differ, and to approve what is moſt excellent. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>Page 12. line 1. for <hi>the,</hi> read <hi>that.</hi> line 10, 11. f. <hi>Author ſaith,</hi> r. <hi>Author's faith.</hi> P. 16. l. 4. r. <hi>of Chriſt.</hi> P. 19. in the 2 laſt lines, from <hi>paſs</hi> to, ought all to be left out until thou comeſt to line 18 of pag. 20. the Articles about Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> P. 20. l. 19. r. <hi>concerning.</hi> P. 27. l. 24. f. <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinay,</hi> r. <hi>obſtinacy.</hi> P. 43. l. 5. f <hi>therein; I readily &amp;c.</hi> r. <hi>wherein I &amp;c.</hi> P. 44. the quotations <hi>p.</hi> 122, 123. in l. 17. are to be applied to l. 13 &amp; 14. P. 56. l. 13. r. <hi>inſtructi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> l. <hi>ult.</hi> f. &amp; 1. <hi>Luke.</hi> P. 63. l. 3. r. <hi>cannot but wonder.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:97824:63"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Books</hi> Printed for <hi>Francis Smith</hi> at the Elephant and Caſtle near the <hi>Royal Exchange</hi> in <hi>Cornhil.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>A New and Uſeful <hi>Concordance</hi> to the <hi>Bible,</hi> with the chief Acceptations, and various Significations contained therein. Alſo <hi>marks</hi> to diſtinguiſh the Commands, Promiſes and Threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings; with a Collection of thoſe Scripture-Propheſies which relate to the Call of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and the Glory that ſhall be in the latter dayes: To which is now added, near Nine Thouſand Scriptures, omitted in the former Edition, with the Addition alſo of the Scripture-Similies and Synonimous Phraſes Alphabetically digeſted; With the Collection of the Names and Titles given to Jeſus Chriſt, and the Appellation given to the Church of God in the Scriptures. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended to the ſtudious Chriſtian, by Dr. <hi>Owen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Treatiſe of Baptiſm;</hi> wherein that of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers and that of Infants, is examined by the Scriptures, with the Hiſtory of both out of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity, making it appear, That Infants-baptiſm
<pb facs="tcp:97824:64"/>
was not practiſed for 300 years, nor enjoyned as neceſſary by the Popes Canons 400 years af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Chriſt, with the fabulous Traditions and Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous Grounds upon which, it with Goſſips, Chriſoms, Exorciſms, Conſignations, Baptizing of Churches &amp; Bells, and other Popiſh Rites are founded: and that the famous <hi>Waldenſian</hi> and old <hi>Brittiſh</hi> Churches and <hi>Chriſtians</hi> witneſſed againſt it; with the Examination of the ſtories of <hi>Thomas Munſter</hi> and <hi>John of Leyden.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Symptoms of Growth,</hi> and <hi>Decay in Godlineſs;</hi> in 80 ſigns of a Living and Dying Chriſtian, with the Cauſes of Decay, and Remedies for Recovery.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Schollar's Companion:</hi> Or, a little Libra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, containing all the Interpretations of Hebrew and Greek words in the <hi>Bible,</hi> both in Latine and Engliſh in great variety, by means whereof the unlearned may eaſily attain unto the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Holy Scriptures in their Original Tongues; a Work very uſeful for every uſeful Chriſtian.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Truth's Champion;</hi> wherein are made plain theſe particulars: Firſt, That Chriſt died for all: Of his Power given out to all: Of Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Of Predeſtination: Of Baptiſm, &amp;c. The Copy of which Book was found hid in an old Wall near <hi>Colcheſter</hi> in <hi>Eſſex.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Scripture-Redemption, freed from Men's Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriction;</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:97824:64"/>
being the ſubſtance of ſeveral Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences about the Death of our Dear Redeemer, and the Controverſies which are the Conſtant Concomitants of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Mystery of Aſtronomy,</hi> made plain to the meaneſt Capacity, by an Arithmetical Deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Coeleſtial and Terreſtrial Globes, by way of <hi>Queſtions</hi> and <hi>Anſwers;</hi> The Wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Works of God from the Earth his Footſtool to the Throne of Heaven; with Divine Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations on every part.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Popiſh Labyrinth;</hi> wherein is made mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, that the Papiſts are intangled in the Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Articles of their Faith, that the Church cannot Err: Written in <hi>Dutch</hi> by that Holy and Learned man, Dr. <hi>Simon Epiſcopius.</hi> To which is added, The Life and Death of the Author.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
